<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the union of the four famous kingdoms of England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland wherein is demonstrated that by the prowess and prudence of the English, those four distinct and discordant nations have upon several conquests been entirely united and devolved into one commonwealth, and that by the candor of clemency and deduction of colonies, alteration of laws, and communication of language, according to the Roman rule, they have been maintained &amp; preserved in peace and union / by a Lover of truth and his country.</title>
            <author>M. H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H91B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19349080</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19349080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1672:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the union of the four famous kingdoms of England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland wherein is demonstrated that by the prowess and prudence of the English, those four distinct and discordant nations have upon several conquests been entirely united and devolved into one commonwealth, and that by the candor of clemency and deduction of colonies, alteration of laws, and communication of language, according to the Roman rule, they have been maintained &amp; preserved in peace and union / by a Lover of truth and his country.</title>
                  <author>M. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Brewster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649 [i.e. 1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: M.H.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [22].</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 125 misnumbered 126.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE UNION Of the four famous Kingdoms Of ENGLAND, WALES, SCOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND and IRELAND.</p>
            <p>Wherein is demonſtrated that by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſs and prudence of the Engliſh, thoſe four diſtinct and diſcordant Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, have upon ſeveral conqueſts been entirely united and devolved into one Commonwealth, and that by the candor of clemency, and deduction of Colonies, alteration of Laws, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Language, according to the Roman rule, they have been main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained &amp; preſerved in peace and union.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Ruis ille tam coufidens, aut tautis cervicibus, qui audeat hiſteriam uſquequaque veram ſcribere?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lipſ. l. 5. c. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Qui non libere veritatem pronunciat, proditor veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſt?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cok. l. 11. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By a lover of truth and his Country.</p>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three Bibles at the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>end of <hi>Paul</hi>'s. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>William Lenthall</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker of the PARLIAMENT of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is aſcribed to Sir <hi>William Paulet</hi> for Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that in four ſeveral Kings and Queens reigns, which were obnoxious to perillous Innovations, he demeaned
<pb facs="tcp:108759:3"/>himſelf ſo obſervantly and cautiouſly in thoſe tempeſtuous and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous times, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly held his head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove water and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his advancement, when numerous Noble perſonages were plunged in their abyſs: And have not there happened al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many pernicious mutations and factions within theſe four years in this State, as were in the Roman Republique for the ſpace of five hundred? wherein your Honour hath ſo circumſpectly and
<pb facs="tcp:108759:3"/>vigilantly ſteered your courſe, that you have not only ſhunned ſhipwrack, which many others did ſuffer, but have alſo fixed your bottom in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of felicity, and at this preſent with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and approbation of all men, do ſit at the helm of this Commonwealth.</p>
            <q>Iſtuc eſt ſapere, qui ubicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> opus ſit animum poſſit flectere.<note place="margin">Terent. Hecyr.</note>
            </q>
            <p>And the Author cordially wiſheth that you may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Will. Paulet</hi> live within 3 years of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</note> if not exceed the years of that famous Councellor of State, that
<pb facs="tcp:108759:4"/>(as he did) by your grave direction and ſage advice to the great Council of this Commonwealth, and by its provident reſolves, Tranquillity and peace may be ſetled in theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a firm Union eſtabliſhed and preſerved in them. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Author hath been induced to preſent to your Honour this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polite Hiſtory concerning the Union of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as <hi>Marcus Terentius Varro</hi> did his Book <hi>de ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine linguae Latinae</hi> to <hi>Marcus Tullius Cicero,</hi> not
<pb facs="tcp:108759:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>by way of inſtruction to admoniſh you, but by way of reference to be cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by you as an equal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator, whether it be worthy of the publique light, and may tend to the publique good, which is the butt &amp; burthen of his labours; wherein he hath had an eſpecial care accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his skill; that as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libius</hi> preſcribeth <hi>ſoli</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bentati litaret,</hi> he ſhould ſacrifice ſolely to truth; and that neither for any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſter conceit he ſhould detract from any, or for any favourable reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:108759:5"/>flatter any, but to pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait every perſon accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his juſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And if it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that in ſome paſſages he hath acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſlipped, ſeeing he hath endeavoured to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend the higher and ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places, he hopeth well that your Honour will be pleaſed to pardon his ſlips and over-ſights, they proceeding from imbecillity and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacy, and to cover them with his good intentione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that you will be as equal towards him, as he is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:108759:5"/>the great God, whom he knoweth not to have given all things to one man. So be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the Almighty to lengthen your days to the great good of this Commonwealth, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively taketh his leave.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt devoted Servant. <hi>M. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:6"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt men are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally prone to applaud the times behind them, and to vilifie the preſent, as the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Hoc hodie ingenium eſt multis,<note place="margin">Clapmar.</note> ut tempora priſca</l>
                  <l>Anteferant noſtris, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum laudentque quod abſit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:7"/>
            <p>And upon the diſlike of every preſent Government are deſirous of a change &amp; like the fiſh <hi>Sepia</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all the waters wherein they live:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> whereas all Government is of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether Monarchical, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocratical, or Democrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21.</note> who at his pleaſure changeth the times and fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and removeth and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up Kings; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought all Gods people to ſubmit and vail to his irreſiſtible will, and to be obedient to the preſent God vernment introduced by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> providence: whence may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:108759:7"/>inferred, that thoſe are of a ſerpentine and diveliſh diſpoſition, who by ſeducing pamphlets, and captious conceits, imploy their turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirits to ſcatter the ſeeds of ſedition, and to foment commotions in ſuch novel ſtates, not with an intention of the publick good, as they gloriouſly pretend, but to make way for their peculiar intereſt and preſumptuous prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; wherein doubtleſs <hi>Coelum irritant armis,</hi> they vainly make War with Heaven, and irritate the divine vengeance to their
<pb facs="tcp:108759:8"/>diſmal confuſion, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to fiſh in ſuch Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian and troubled waters, <hi>Saepe piſcatores capti ſunt</hi> are commonly catched in their own net, and like am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious bees drowned in their own honey. Examples of which we need not ſeek from forraign parts, our Nation affording too many, who through ſuch deſperate and dangerous inſurrectious have wrought the ruine of their generations and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and not to ſpeak of the laſt combuſtion which is like to produce the ſame effects and forfeitures, the
<pb facs="tcp:108759:8"/>Author wiſheth in General <hi>Quodicti piſcatores ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,</hi> that being ſtruck with this Scorpion they may cautiouſly avoid the like danger, and wiſely ſhun ſuch deſtructive pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices: for it is not his drift to trample on the afflicted, nor to upbraid any one with the commemoration of their preterit exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but to draw every one within the circumference and liſt of peace, amity, and union. For what an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and inhumane ſpectacle hath it been, and ſtill is to fee, that the Engliſh Nation
<pb facs="tcp:108759:9"/>which hath alwaies been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted fierce againſt their foes, and faithful to their friends, ſhall now become more fierce and faithleſs one againſt another, and ſheath their ſwords in their own bowels; ſuch an unſociable and unnatural War, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the extirpation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble families and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deſtruction of the whole Nation. Wherefore for our own and countryes ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, be exhorted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (that whereas by the unanimous valour and conſtant circumſpection of the Engliſh thoſe three va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
<pb facs="tcp:108759:9"/>Nations of <hi>Wales, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> have been totally vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and entirely united into one Commonwealth with <hi>England,</hi> and at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent made a firm quaternity and invincible phalanx a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all forraign Forces) to ſet aſide all civil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and diſcontents, and to remove them as far from us.</p>
            <q>Quantum Hyſpanis Ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to diſſidet Eridano,</q>
            <p>As far as <hi>Scythia</hi> diſſides from <hi>Italy,</hi> or <hi>Spain</hi> from
<pb facs="tcp:108759:10"/>
               <hi>Britanny,</hi> and to bend and unite our national Forces againſt our forraign and outlandiſh Enemies, that thereby we may live in unity and ſafety among our ſelves. For as we are inſtructed by Philoſophy, that there are two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all things, <hi>Concord</hi> and <hi>Diſcord,</hi> the one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſolving and conſuming all things; ſo are we taught by it's Miſtreſs Experience that petty ſtates are by Concord and union augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and grand ones by Diſcord and Diſunion
<pb facs="tcp:108759:10"/>brought to confuſion, as the Poet preſsly.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Diſcordia gaudet Permiſcere fretu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coelo.<note place="margin">Sil. Ital.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vale atque his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:11"/>
            <head>Ode Triumphalis Ad laté Dominantem Angliam:</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANguſta laurus palma<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vilior,</l>
               <l>Quaecunque priſcis gratia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus,</l>
               <l>Sordeſoat ad famam potentis,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Angliae</hi> &amp; indomici Britanni.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jam <hi>Roma</hi> pallet, jam ſtupet ardua</l>
               <l>Incoepta noſtrum, <hi>Caeſaris</hi> &amp; pudet,</l>
               <l>Nunc irritos dolens labores</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Agricolain</hi> tacet &amp; <hi>Severum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quocunque vertis terribilem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</l>
               <l>(O Diis amata &amp; gens celeberrima)</l>
               <l>Spiſſaeque dehiſcunt Phalanges</l>
               <l>Et trepidae recidunt catervae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dii Terminales</hi> ſedibus exulant</l>
               <l>Ariſque cedunt quas ſibi ſaecula</l>
               <l>Ignota rite conſecrarunt</l>
               <l>Atque tuum fugiunt <hi>Triumphum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fatis negatam pergere, gloria</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:108759:11"/>
               <l>Honor<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtri Temporis, invidam</l>
               <l>Tranſgreſſus en tandem <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aſſeruit metuendus, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neptunus alto ſtridet in aequore</l>
               <l>Tethyſque late brachia porrigit</l>
               <l>Nymphas ut omnes conſalutet,</l>
               <l>Limite nec remoratur ullo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Se prima victam plorat <hi>Hibernia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et mox Hiberno <hi>Cantaber</hi> additus</l>
               <l>Poſt rupta pacis bellique jura</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fadifragus</hi> luit inde <hi>Scotus</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Laetatur <hi>Anglus</hi> jam numero pari</l>
               <l>Cui regna ſubſunt quatuor, annuant</l>
               <l>His Fata, <hi>quatuor</hi> ut per orbis</l>
               <l>Promoveat ſua ſceptra <hi>Partes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic Vaticinatur. J. H. Stu. Eccl. Chr. Oxon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:12"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 3 line 21. read <hi>abuſed.</hi> p. 20. l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dele <hi>and.</hi> P. 35. l. 19. for <hi>praefecto,</hi> r. <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecte</hi> ibid. l. 22. for they, r. <hi>that.</hi> p 48. l. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for fellows, r. <hi>followers.</hi> p. 51. l. 3. r. <hi>reprob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> p. 53. l. 14. r. <hi>and is.</hi> p. 80 l. 1. r. <hi>thereth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> p. 110 l. 19. r. <hi>and ſo.</hi> P. 14. l. 2. for affinity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſerenity of air.</hi> ibid. l. 18. r. <hi>Iſlands.</hi> p. 117 l. 21. dele in the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108759:12"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF The four famous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, ENGLAND, WALES, SCOTLAND, and IRELAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nion is the ornament and muniment of the Univerſe, which is ſo orderly and cloſely conjoyned, as no vacuity or breach is therein admittable, which maks it ſo perpetual; for which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly union it is by the Septuagint called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and by the Latins <hi>Mundus</hi> that is beautiful. For order and union adorn all things, for which reaſon that glorious and orderly Artifice is by the holy Ghoſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108759:13"/>Ailed an Hoſt, or Army, and as the vulgar tranſlation truely terms it, <hi>Exercitus: Itaque perfectiſunt coeli, &amp; tarrae, &amp; exercitus corum;</hi> for no battles or phalanx can be more firmly rank'd and united, or better governed (as <hi>Delrius</hi> on that place paraphraſeth) then the creatures in Heaven and Earth are diſpoſed knit together and ruled: and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo comely or conſtant, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ready and obedient to their Creator, and King, at whoſe word and wink they take Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the impious, and (in a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly poſture) unite themſelves to fight his battles; when, as the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaith,<note place="margin">Wiſdom. s. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> he is pleaſed to make his creatures his weapons for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of his enemies.</p>
            <p>And as the divine power is the general Architector of union in the frame of the univerſe, ſo is he the particular Author of order, and anion among men; to whom (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Sublunary creatures) he communicated his ſimilitude, and natural inclination to order, ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108759:13"/>and unity: For after the Lord God had framed man of the duſt of the ground, (or of red earth, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> expoundeth it,<note place="margin">Joſeph Antiq. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> whence he was called <hi>Adam</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies red,) and inſtilled and breathed into him his own image; and then alſo made him the Monarch and Lord of all the world, ſubjecting all things to his power, order, and dominion, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 8.</note> 
               <hi>omniae ſubjecit pedibus ejus,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards conjoyned unto him as an Adjutor, like unto himſelf, the woman as his Aſſociate: From which equality did proceed a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon power to the man and wife over their family,<note place="margin">Tholoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> which is called <hi>Domeſtica poteſtas,</hi> or <hi>oeconomia,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Offices of each <hi>Sex:</hi> But becauſe the woman abuſe her common power and wrought miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thief to the man, ſhe was (for the ſuture) made ſubject to the man, and the man had <hi>Maritalis poteſtas</hi> over the woman. And it is not to at doubted but that if <hi>Adam</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted in his integrity, and being
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108759:14"/>confirmed, had multiplyed his generations, but that God who is <hi>Pater ordinis,</hi> would that in order one to the other, there ſhould have been an inferiour,<note place="margin">Paraeus in <hi>Gen. 1. 28.</hi>
               </note> and a ſuperiour And that <hi>Adam</hi> who was <hi>Pater om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Viventium</hi> ſhould have a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal power over all mankind, by the law of nature, as over a great family, and that there ſhould have been a civil dominion, and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but altogether voluntary and comfortable; and a <hi>Politeia</hi> and government, and a decent order and union among men without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſervile conſtraint, or coercion according to the law of nature in which thoſe that ruled ſhould freely adviſe, and thoſe who were ſubject ſhould freely obey, and no that one man ſhould lord it, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> domineer over another. For ſuch lording rule and ſervile ſubjection were introduced after the fall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Adam,</hi> when ſervitude began to be a juſt puniſhment for ſin, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> force and fraud (the venemo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſeeds of ſin) bad ſpread themſelve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108759:14"/>over the face of the earth; when latrocinies, and rapines, murthers, and homicides raigned in the hearts and hands of men, and threatned deſtruction to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the ſword of each devouring other, which cauſed a ſeparation and diſunion among the Sons of Men. Then <hi>neceſſity</hi> brought in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive and controling dominion, which by the ſword and force might curb and reſtrain ſuch malefactors from perpetrating ſuch violent and inhumane injuries; and either to puniſh them with death, or reduce them to a civil life and union.<note place="margin">Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome Muſculus Cornelius de lapide. Paraeus <hi>Geneſ. 10.</hi>
               </note> To which purpoſe God raiſed <hi>Nimrod (for all power is of God)</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling others in vigour of body and virtue of mind, by his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and relief to ſuch injured and abuſed perſons, procured to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a potent Army, with which he ſubdued all the lawleſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous routs and multitudes. And therefore is he ſaid to be a mighty hunter before the Lord, not onely becauſe he excelled in might,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108759:15"/>but becauſe that he <hi>nutu &amp; ductu Dei</hi> through the divine impulſe, and conduct, did ſubject the rude and barbarous Nations to the ſway of his Scepter, and ſtoutly rul'd them by the power of his ſword;<note place="margin">Petavius ration. Tomp. lib. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>100.</hi>
               </note> who of the heathen writers is called <hi>Belus,</hi> as by ours <hi>Nimred,</hi> and affirmed to be the ſame man that did build the Tower, and took upon him a new Empire over rude people as <hi>Petavius</hi> obſerveth:<note place="margin">Teſtatus in Geneſ. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> He alſo by <hi>Teſtatus</hi> is ſaid to be the firſt King, becauſe we read in holy Writ of none who reigned before him;<note place="margin">Petavius ib.</note> and by other Hiſtorians that he was the founder and hood of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Empire, and was the firſt that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed many barbarous Nations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the civil and moral body of one Commonwealth:<note place="margin">Grotius de J. B. &amp; P. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>Grotius, plurium populorum idem poteſt eſſe caput,</hi> there may be one head of many people, which ſingle people notwithſtanding have a perfect commonalty: for it is not in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral body as in a natural, where there cannot be one head of many
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108759:15"/>bodies, but in a moral body the ſame perſon may be head of many diſtinct bodies: And it were to be wiſhed that the whole world were governed by one head in unity as it ſhould have been by <hi>Adam</hi> if he had perſevered in his perſection. But ſin by his delinquency entring into the world, hath ſown the ſeeds of diſcord among all Nations, that ſince one head could never be eſtabliſhed over them all, nor an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſetled by the moſt potent and ſageſt Princes and people, though ſome have had the ambition to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect it; and one vainely wiſhed that there were more worlds to conquer and yet could not ſettle two Kingdoms in union; for ſo perverſe &amp; crooked are all Nations and ſo prone to diſcordancy and martial occurrents, that no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſs nor prudence can continually contain them in obedience and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, nor no compact nor league can preſerve them in mutual amity, but that they will upon ſome feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pretence break out into im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108759:16"/>Wars and martial defiances which is an Epidemical and incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable contagion in this world, as it is Emphatically and divinely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Prince of Poets.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quippe ubi fas verſum atque nefas tot bella per orbem.<note place="margin">Virg. Georg. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Tam multae ſcelerum facies, non ullus aratro,</l>
               <l>Dignus bones, ſqualent abductis arva colonis,</l>
               <l>Et curvae rigidum falces conflan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in enſem,</l>
               <l>Hine movet Euphrates, illinc Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania bellum,</l>
               <l>Vicinae ruptis interſe legibus ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</l>
               <l>Arma ferunt, ſaevit tate Mars im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius orbe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Howſoever, though it be an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt above poſſibility to reduce all Nations into a conformable uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet is it an heroical, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enterpriſe ſo far as may be to proceed in bringing it to perfection that thereby the leſſe rapins, blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheds
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108759:16"/>and ſlaughters may happen between them, and at the leaſt in ſome parts of this Orb there may be a reſemblance of another Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe for peace and union on earth. And for ſuch atchievments many victorious <hi>Heroes</hi> have received immortal praiſe and glory, and are regiſtred in the monuments of ſame, as <hi>Nimrod, Ninus, Joſhua, David, Cyrus, Alexander,</hi> and the martial <hi>Romans.</hi> Seing then it is ſuch a Divine and noble action to unite divided Nations it is worthy our ſtudy and diligence to examine by what means it may be obtained: and though the Author finds no beaten path to follow, nor publick pattern to imitate, yet it may be collected out of Claſſick Authors, that there are three common prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by which Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths have been inſtructed to enterpriſe that deſign.</p>
            <p>The firſt is by leagues, of which in Commonwealths there is great neceſſity and utility,<note place="margin">Scor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerius Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>unita vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fortior, &amp; hoſti terribilior,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108759:17"/>by the mutual conjunction of their minds, the one may in danger aſſiſt the other and defend each other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their enemies; and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called peace when by treaties and agreements it is made and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, which was in prime pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe among the <hi>Romans,</hi> and very profitable unto them. For as <hi>Dion</hi> ſaith, they by imparting aid to their friends and confederates obtained the Empire of the whole world;<note place="margin">Flor. li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> the reaſon of which <hi>Florus</hi> giveth, <hi>Quiae ſummae faederum Romanis religie fuit,</hi> for that the <hi>Romaus</hi> very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly and devoutly obſerved their leagues. A notable example of which we have in <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> whom <hi>Tulius Hoſtilius</hi> for breaking of a league commanded to be bound faſt between two Chariots,<note place="margin">Floras I. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and drawn in pieces by ſwift and violent horſes. A formideble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of which in ſacred writ, we alſo read: as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Juceb</hi> were curſed by their father at his denth, for that thy had violated their league made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108759:17"/>with <hi>Sichem</hi> and <hi>Hemor</hi> when they deſtroyed them and all their City contrary to their covenant.<note place="margin">Geneſ. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> In like manner the puniſhment of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Sauls</hi> poſterity was memorable for his breach of league, which <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> made with the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> when as three hundred yeers after <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſeaven of <hi>Sauls</hi> children and family were delivered into the hands of the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and crucified by them in puniſhment of <hi>Sauls</hi> offence. And though leagues among all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be honourable, and ſacroſanct and not to be violated by humane and divine Laws, yet are they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly but temporary and for a time; and made for utility and not for amity. For as <hi>Livy, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis utilitas oſt nodus, &amp; vinculum federis,</hi> common utility is the knot and band of league. And as the ſocieties of men were firſt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for utility, ſo are the unions by leagnes for utilities ſake, which failing, that band and knot is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or cut in ſunder. And there are too many Machivilians in theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108759:18"/>latter and impious times, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low perfidiouſneſs and breach of faith in Princes, and that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſomtimes for the benefit of a ſtate; which makes the unions by leagues to be leſſe permanent and obnoxius to mutability, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the aforefaid complaint of the ingenious Poet.</p>
            <q>Vicinae ruptis inter ſe legibus urbes Arma ferunt.<note place="margin">Virg. Georg. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond union of Kingdomes is compaſſed by marriages and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,<note place="margin">Clapmar. de arc. imp. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> &amp; therefore as an acute Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Matrimoniorum maguorum principum maxima cura eſſe debet.</hi> There ought to be the greateſt care of the marriages of great Princes, for that from them Wars begin and again ceaſe, and unions of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes by ſuch deſcents ſometimes happen: But ſuch unions alſo are not frequent, nor many times ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſtant. And though the Kingdome of <hi>Spain</hi> and Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> have had the felicity to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108759:18"/>flouriſh for many years by ſuch unions and affinities, yet hath <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> lately fallen from them, and the reſt may be ſuppoſed not to be perpetual. And in the moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> are ſuch titles of deſcent, claiming by the faeminine ſex, barred by the law <hi>Salique</hi> which was made by <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> King of the <hi>Franconians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tholoſanus Syntag. lib. <hi>45.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and amended by <hi>Clodoreus, Childericus</hi> and <hi>Lotharius;</hi> by reaſon of which law alwaies in the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> as the <hi>Franconians</hi> inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the iſſue male, the female iſſue being excluded, have held the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Which law and cuſtome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been controverted hath been divers times by ſentence confirmed, and by arms and reaſons approved. Eſpecially againſt <hi>Edward</hi> the third King of <hi>England,</hi> who for that he drew his pedigree by a female (though he was the nearer in blood;) <hi>Philip. le Bell</hi> (the next Heir Male) was by the law <hi>Salique,</hi> preferred before him: which excluding fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males was adjudged to exclude all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108759:19"/>the deſcendents by females, and therefore was <hi>Philip</hi> received and crowned King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third, becauſe his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was not then ſetled, and he but young, did homage to King <hi>Philip</hi> for the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Guyen</hi> and other territories in <hi>France:</hi> though afterwards when he had arrived to the years of maturity and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, upon more mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the partial interpretation of that law and the inſtigation of the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Artois</hi> (a great Peer of <hi>France</hi>) affirming that he had more right to that Crown then the other, he by Armes attempted to recover and conjoyn that Kingdome to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> and by his invincible ſword obtained many wondrous victories. But he yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Fate before he had accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed his intention, his ſucceſſors <hi>Henry</hi> the 5th. and <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. renewed the ſaid honourable War, and by their victorious Armes ſo prevailed, that <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. was Crowned in <hi>Paris</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108759:19"/>and had finiſh'd that glorious work, whereby the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> had been annexed and united to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> but that the civil Wars between the houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> in <hi>England</hi> impeded the ſame, as <hi>Philippus Comineus</hi> (Secretary to <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th. King of <hi>France</hi>) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly acknowledgeth; by which diſaſter the hopeful union of the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England</hi> by marriage, unhappily was prevented and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>And as for the inconſtancy and deficiency of ſuch unions. I will onely inſtance in one which was thought moſt happy and durable in this Nation; and that was the union of the two famous Kingdomes of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>James</hi> the 6. King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who was by marriage lineally deſcended of the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> Eldeſt Daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th. King of <hi>England,</hi> and Eldeſt Siſter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. Father
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108759:20"/>of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> by whoſe deceaſe ſhe being the laſt of iſſue of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England</hi> did lineally and rightfully deſcend to the ſaid <hi>James</hi> King of <hi>Scetland,</hi> by which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conjunction thoſe two diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Kingdomes of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> were fortunately and peaceably united under one impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown.</p>
            <p>An union magnified, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded of both Nations, and yet not laſting above one deſcent; The <hi>Scotch</hi> revolting firſt, and then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to the confuſion of both Kingdomes, and changing them both into one Commonwealth; which verifies the <hi>Italian</hi> proverb: <hi>Kings may wed, but Kingdoms never.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third union of Kingdomes is by conqueſt, which is moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and more durable. For as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> the moſt part of unious and plantations of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Commonwealths have been founded by conqueſt which is manifeſted as well by forraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108759:20"/>Annals as by native occurrences, as by the ſequel will appear. But not to entrench upon your patience by the tedious relations of the unions of Nations which were made by the conqueſts of the <hi>Aſſyrians, Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Graecians;</hi> I will inſiſt only on thoſe that were gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the glorious ſword of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> which for extent and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſurpaſſed all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Roman Commonwealth,</hi> and Empire for the extents and dignity of it, is by the <hi>Civilians</hi> called <hi>Caput &amp; ſedes imperii orbis,</hi> and by <hi>Athaeneus</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the head, ſeat, and Epitome of the Empire of the whole world, according to the verſe.</p>
            <q>Orbem jam totum victor Romanus habebat.</q>
            <p>And therefore did the Emperors ſometimes ſtile themſelves <hi>Domini mundi,</hi> the Lords of the world,<note place="margin">Grotius de J. B. &amp; P. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> which ſpeeches though <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith are <hi>per exceſſum &amp; excellentiam
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108759:21"/>dicta,</hi> ſpoken by the exceſs and excellency,<note place="margin">Bodin de Repub. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Bodin</hi> that in <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jans</hi> time when it moſt flouriſhed <hi>Vix trigeſſimam orbis terrarum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem complecti potuiſſet,</hi> it ſcarce could contain the thirtieth part of the whole earth, yet it is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to none but that it did contain the beſt and moſt flouriſhing parts of <hi>Europe, Africa,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> in <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> time,<note place="margin">Patritius de Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cujus ſolum nomen Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorum &amp; Indorum Reges ſomnum capere non ſiuebat:</hi> whoſe fame on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would not permit the Kings of the <hi>Parthians</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> to ſleep which were the remoteſt parts of <hi>Aſia;</hi> at which time the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> was in its youthful ſtrength and robuſt maturity as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith. <hi>Hic jam ipſa juventa imperii, &amp; quaſi quaedam robuſta maturitas.</hi> But to demonſtrate how by degrees it row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up to ſuch a vaſt greatneſs; and firſt becauſe commonly irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conteſts, and contentions hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen between vicine and bordering Nations as the Poet.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108759:21"/>
            <q>
               <l>Inter finitimes vetus atque antiqua ſimultas,<note place="margin">Juven Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Immortale odium, &amp; nunquam ſanabile vulnus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> did firſt augment their ſtate, by the conqueſt and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of their neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries as <hi>Ninus</hi> did,<note place="margin">Juſtin l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui primus bellum intulit finitimis,</hi> who firſt made War with the borderers, and ſo as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Caeſar. l. <hi>6.</hi> de Bello Gallico.</note> did the <hi>Germans</hi> who deemed it <hi>proprium virtutis,</hi> an eſpecial virtue to expel their neighbors from their fields, and not ſuffer them to dare to conſiſt near them. For ſo ſaith he did they think themſelves more ſafe <hi>repentinae incurſionis timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſublato,</hi> the fear of ſudden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions being taken away, for which reaſon <hi>Danaeus</hi> propounds this for an Aphoriſme.<note place="margin">Danaeus Aphoriſm fo. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vicini populi nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am creſcentis potentta mature eſt quacunque occaſione deprimenda.</hi> The power of a too-much-increaſing neighbour is ſpeedily upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to be ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Which therefore was the conſtant
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108759:22"/>courſe the <hi>Romans</hi> ſteered, in their firſt march to ſubdue their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent neighbours, and by which work they made way for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the other parts of the world. For after they within the ſpace of five hundred years, with much difficulty had brought into ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the <hi>Sabins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florns l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Albanes,</hi> the <hi>Latines,</hi> and all other the adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning people of <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſo became <hi>Caput Italiae</hi> &amp; within the two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years following, with their victorious arms did they overcome <hi>Africa, Europe, Aſia,</hi> and all the world, and were therefore worthily intituled <hi>Caput totius orbis terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Romans</hi> by valour did ſubdue their enemies bodies, ſo by their wiſdome did they ſubjugate their minds, which was the greateſt victory, and by degrees reduced them into a ſociable union with them, and of enemies made them their friends and Citizens. As <hi>Claudius</hi> in <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Romulus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. Aun. l. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conditor noſter Romuſus tanta ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiâ
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108759:22"/>valuit, ut plereſque populos co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem die hoſtes, dein cives habuerit.</hi> Our founder <hi>Romulus</hi> was of ſo great wiſdome that the ſame day he handled the ſame people as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and then intreated them as Citizens.<note place="margin">Liv. li. <hi>1.</hi> Flor. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And ſo <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Florus</hi> relate of <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi> that after he had ſubjected the <hi>Albans</hi> which a long time before were a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and principal Enemy, he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined and diſmantled <hi>Alba,</hi> and tranferred and carried away all the goods, and the people themſelves to <hi>Rome,</hi> by which the number of the Citizens was doubled, <hi>ita ut prorſus in ſuum corpus rediiſſe rurſus videretur:</hi> ſo that it altogether ſeemed again to have returned into its own body. Many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are extant in the Hiſtories of the <hi>Sabins, Latins,</hi> and others of <hi>Italy,</hi> which as <hi>Cicero</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Balbus</hi> ſaith, was the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>Illud certe ſine dubitatione noſtrum funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit imperium, &amp; populi Romani
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108759:23"/>nomen auxit quod princeps, &amp; crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor urbis noſtrae Romulus foedere Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ino docuit, etiam hoſtibus recipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis augeri hanc civitatem oportere, cujus authoritate &amp; exemplo nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam eſt intermiſſa à majoribus noſtris largitio, &amp; communicatio civitatis.</hi> That without all doubt did chiefly lay the foundation of the Empire, and augment the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, that the Prince, and Creator, of our City, <hi>Romulus,</hi> did by the <hi>Sabine</hi> league inſtruct, that alſo this City ought to be increaſed by receiving enemies by whoſe authority and example the largition and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the City was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted or diſcontinued by our anceſtors. For after <hi>Cicero</hi>'s time, the Emperours of <hi>Rome</hi> did not onely grant their liberties and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges to particular perſons, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and houſes, but to whole Cities,<note place="margin">Vide Coke, lib. <hi>7.</hi> Calv. caſe fo. <hi>24.</hi> a.</note> and Conntries, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by the plea of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 21. and 22. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> That he was a <hi>Roman</hi> by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108759:23"/>naturalization, though he was a <hi>Jew</hi> by Nation, and becauſe he was born at <hi>Tarſus</hi> in <hi>Cilicia</hi> under the obedience of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours he was by birth a Citizen of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that therefore it was allowed unlawful for the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune</hi> to ſcourge him being a <hi>Roman</hi> and uncondemned, and for the ſame reaſon, not long after, his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>Caeſar</hi> was admitted by <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus;</hi> which is alſo cleared by the conſtitution of <hi>Antonine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> by which as many as were in <hi>Orbe Romano</hi> within the Roman Globe, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that Empire were made Roman Citizens,<note place="margin">Grotius de I.B. &amp; P. lib. <hi>2. c. 9.</hi>
               </note> and as <hi>Grotius</hi> faith, obtained the ſame rights which the Colonies and Municipies and provinces had. So as they were capable of honours and did make uſe of the rights and priviledges of the Romans. Nay before his age, <hi>Caeſar</hi> the founder of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire not onely admitted ſuch alien enemies into the City but alſo honoured them with the Senators Robe, as it is ſaid, <hi>Caeſar
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108759:24"/>Gallos in Triumphum duxit, idem in Curiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when under the Empire of <hi>Claudius</hi> the queſtion was agitated concerning the ſupplement of the Senate, and that the chief of the <hi>Gaules</hi> called <hi>Comata,</hi> having gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the entercourſe and freedom of the Roman City, did much deſire alſo the priviledge of obtaining the honours of that City;<note place="margin">Tac. Ann. l. <hi>11.</hi> fo. <hi>228.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Multus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus,</hi>) <hi>ſuper care varius rnmor, &amp; ſtudiis diverſis apud principent certabatur,</hi> There was a great and various report touching that matter, which with diverſity of ſtudies and opinions was diſputed and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted before the Prince; yet upon the accurate oration and diſcuſſion of <hi>Claudius,</hi> the chief of the <hi>Hedues</hi> by the decree of the <hi>Senate,</hi> did obtain the priviledges of Senators in the City: from which conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all Nations under the obedience and rule of this Roman Emperour were accounted but as one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>But though it was an Act above
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108759:24"/>compare &amp; without example, for the <hi>Romans</hi> to conquer ſo many mighty Princes, yet to keep them all in ſubjection, exceedeth admiration; for as judicious <hi>Florus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florus lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Difficilius eſt provincias retinere quam parare,</hi> and ſententious <hi>Seneca, parare &amp; quaerere arduum, tenere difficilius,</hi> to whom the ſecond <hi>Virgil</hi> ſeems to allude.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O faciles dare ſumma deos, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque tueri, <note place="margin">Lucan. l. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Difficiles.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is an high and hard attempt to ſeek and gain provinces, but a more difficult and laborious task to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and retain them; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe no utility will proceed of our ſeekings, and would do nothing elſe but <hi>Cribro haurire</hi> labour in vain. And therefore it is worthy our induſtry to ſearch and inquire by what victories and policies the Romans for ſo many hundred years did keep and retain ſo many ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and ſtout Nations in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108759:25"/>awe, and an uniformity of obedience.</p>
            <p>The prime policy which the Romans uſed to tame a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Nation, and to draw it into a conjuncture and union with them was clemency, which is the proper virtue of an <hi>Heroick</hi> Victor, who Lyon like is clement, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to the devicted. <hi>Satis eſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraſse leoni.</hi> For though the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hath <hi>vitae &amp; necis poteſtatem,</hi> and by the law of War, thoſe who have overcome have power to rule thoſe whom they have overcome, as they pleaſe; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Timoleon</hi> in <hi>Aemilius Probus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eam praeclaram ducendam victoriam in qua plus eſt clementiae quam crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis.</hi> That is to be reputed the moſt renowned victory, in which there is more clemency then eruelty; and <hi>Saluſt,</hi> in his oration to <hi>Caefar, Qui benignitate, &amp; clementia regnum temperavere, his jucunda, &amp; laeta omuia fuerunt, etiam hoſtes aequiores quam illius cives:</hi> whoſoever have tempered their Empire with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108759:25"/>and clemency, to theſe all things were pleaſant and proſperous and their enemies more civil then Citizens. Which was the conſtant courſe of the Romans in all their conqueſts to intreat their enemies honourably;<note place="margin">Juſtin. lib. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and as <hi>Alexander</hi> did <hi>non quaeſi victos, ſed victoriae ſocios habere,</hi> not as ſlaves and ſervants, but as companions and citizens, as hath been before amply and fully declared and therefore ſurceaſe to proſecute this point.</p>
            <p>But though clemency hath a great ſway, among many, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth much to the union of States,<note place="margin">Coke Com. <hi>upon</hi> Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tl. <hi>392. B.</hi>
               </note> yet as Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſaith, <hi>Et ſi meliores ſunt ques ducit amor, tamen plures ſunt ques cogit timor:</hi> Though they be the better whom Love doth draw, yet they are the more whom Fear doth force. And therefore did the <hi>Romans</hi> uſe more powerful and coercive policies then clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that thoſe that would not be allured by courteous, and civil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatments ſhould be compelled by ſevere, and rigorous courſes, as by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108759:26"/>Arms &amp; Laws without which the un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on of Commonwealths or Empire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot conſiſt; for as the aforeſaid <hi>Florus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florus lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viribus parantur, jure reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur,</hi> which therefore I have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced together, becauſe they mutually protect each other,<note place="margin">Juſt. inſtit principio.</note> as <hi>Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Illorum alterum alterius au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio ſemper eget, &amp; tani res militar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> legibus, quam ipſae leges armoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praeſidio ſervatae ſunt,</hi> The o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hath always wanted the aid of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other, and as well military matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are preſerved by Laws, as the Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves by the force of Arms, without which they are but as a dead letter, or as a bell without a clapper, without life or ſound.</p>
            <p>By whoſe mutuall aſſiſtance and power, the Roman Commonwealth and Empire was eſtabliſhed, and maintained in peace and union: And for that reaſon are they by the exquiſite Poet <hi>Claudian</hi> conioyned in his Commendations of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Claudian Stillicon.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Armorum legumque potens quae fundit in omnes</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:108759:26"/>
               <l>Imperium, primique dedit cuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae juris.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But now to treat of them diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, and firſt of armes which ſeem to have the prerogative, as well in the retaining, as in the gaining of an Empire: for as <hi>Saluſt,</hi> the great Judge of matters of State and manners of Men,<note place="margin">Fulb. l. <hi>1.</hi> fo. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> as Mr. <hi>Fulbeck</hi> ſtileth him. <hi>Imperium facile his artibus retinetur, quibus partum eſt,</hi> an Empire is eaſily retained by thoſe Arts it was firſt gained,</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Panſa</hi> and <hi>Hirtius</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Paterculus, ut Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum armis quaeſitum armis teneret,</hi> that he ſhould keep that principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by Arms that he had gotten by Arms, which afterwards he loſt by the diſmiſſion of the Praetorian ſouldiers, and laying his life open to his enemies, periſhed through his clemency and ſecurity; which therefore is called by that elegant Author <hi>Laudandum experieutia Conſilium, A councel commended by experience.</hi> And therefore the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108759:27"/>generally mingled clemency with ſafety, and prudently by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies ſecured themſelves from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent commotions: For uſually upon their conqueſts, did they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately appropriate the ſeventh part of the territories of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, upon old beaten ſouldien in way of remuneration for their faithful ſervice, which was called <hi>Coloniarum deductio,</hi> and the place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf <hi>Romana Colonia;</hi> and as <hi>Seneca, Hic populus</hi> ſpeaking of the Roman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Colonias in omnes provincias miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lypſ. Pol. li. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ubicunque vicit, Romanus habitat.</hi> Which as <hi>Lipſius</hi> ſaith, was <hi>ſolidu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; firmum reſpublicas provehen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> munimentum,</hi> the ſolid and firm for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of promoting Common-wealths. For the Roman Colonie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were fortified with trenches, Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirs and Bulwarks to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the aſſaults of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, &amp; as <hi>Danaeus,</hi> colonies wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not deduced into the fields of the vanquiſhed without great grief,<note place="margin">Danaeut Aphoriſ. fol. <hi>138.</hi>
               </note> and fear of the inhabitants. <hi>Itaq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:108759:27"/>vallis &amp; muris &amp; praeſidio firmandae, nam inſidiis &amp; armis primo quoque tempore ab indigenis petuntur.</hi> And therefore are they to be fortified with trenches, walls, and bulwarks, for eſpecially upon the firſt ſertle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are they by force or fraud aſſaulted by the natives, who natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally abhorring ſervitude, uſe all their ſtratagems to undermine, and overthrow them. And as <hi>Florus</hi> diſertly, <hi>non aſſuetae fraenis ſervitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis tumidae gentium inflataeque cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florus, li. <hi>4. c. 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>facile alias ab impoſito nuper jugo reſilirent.</hi> The ſwelling and arrogant necks of nations not accuſtomed to the reins of ſervitude would eaſily otherwiſe skip back from their new impoſed yoke. As the Germans did, who as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith, were <hi>vieti magis quam domiti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florus. ib.</note> were vanquiſhed rather then tamed,<note place="margin">Vita agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col. jo. <hi>66:.</hi> &amp; Grotius, de J. B. &amp; P. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and in the end <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, did ſhake off the Roman yoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the valor of <hi>Arminius</hi> who defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſlew <hi>Varus</hi> and his legions, and as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, were out of the compaſſe of the Roman Empire
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108759:28"/>whom the <hi>Britans</hi> did alſo ſeem to emulate, who diſdaining the Roman ſervitude, <hi>Domiti ut pareant, non ut ſerviant,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, did ſtoutly attempt, under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of that valiant Queen <hi>Vaodica,</hi> to regain their naturall freedom; and though in that kingdom they had planted their Colonies fortified with walls and caſtles, which they could never attain to in Germany; yet they univerſally concurring in one reſolution, joyntly took Arms, and on a ſuddain did ſet upon the Roman ſouldiers diſperſed in their caſtles, and having beaten them from their forts, invaded the <hi>Colonie</hi> it ſelf as the ſeat of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, and having obtained the victory, omitted no kind of rigor and cruelty; in ſomuch as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, if <hi>Paulinus</hi> had not incontin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently repaired to their reliefe, <hi>amiſſa Britannia foret,</hi> Britanny would have been loſt, and could hardly be ſuppreſſed and reclaym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, untill <hi>Petronius Turpilianus</hi> was ſent by the Senate, a man of a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108759:28"/>milder temper, who by his lenity and clemency compoſed all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and were, from time to time more humanly and freely intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſucceeding Legates, who by their humanity ſo prevailed with them, as many thouſands of the ſtouteſt liſted themſelves in their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and were faithful auxiliaries to them. Inſomuch as when the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans were called from <hi>Britanny</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> to ſuppreſſe the <hi>Huns</hi> who moleſted that Countrey, they were drawn to accompany them in that expedition, and to aſſiſt them in their Battails, and for their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour were gloriouſly planted in that part of <hi>France,</hi> which from their name is called <hi>Brittain.</hi> Thus did the Romans, through the ſweetneſs of their clemency, and rigour of their <hi>Colonies</hi> tranſplanted and diſperſed among their ſubdued Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, keep them in quiet and ſubjection, and reduced them into a ſociable union, which <hi>Colonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scorbore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius polit. lib. <hi>10.</hi> c.</note> as <hi>Scorbonerius</hi> a noble obſerver of the affairs of State, were as it were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108759:29"/>a ſmall effigies and portraiture of the Amplitude and Majeſty of the people of <hi>Rome.</hi> For there were one hundred threeſcore and three Colonies deduced and diſperſed among the Roman Provinces, which did ſway and rule them by their power, and juriſdiction; and as Learned and Laborious Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> ſaith, it is clear that divers Colonies deduced from <hi>Rome</hi> were in <hi>Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Foiteſ. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fo. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Of which he rendereth the names of four, in which as Sir <hi>John Baker</hi> Hiſtorieth it,<note place="margin">Fol. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained no fewer then fourſcore thouſand Souldiers in pay.</p>
            <q>Tuntae molis erat Romanam conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gentem</q>
            <p>Now followeth the impoſition of Laws, for though they <hi>inter arma ſilent,</hi> yet after victory and conqueſt they conduce much to the union of Nations, which the Romans alſo uſed for the compleating of the ſame. and this is a prerogative inſeparably incident to a conquerour, to give
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108759:29"/>and impoſe Laws on the conquered,<note place="margin">Coke li. <hi>7.</hi> Calv. caſe fo. <hi>17.</hi> B.</note> as <hi>Alexander</hi> in <hi>Curtius, Leges a victoribus dari, accipi a victis.</hi> Of which Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> giveth this reaſon, That ſeeing he that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to a Kingdom by conqueſt, hath <hi>vitae &amp; necis poteſtatem,</hi> he may at his pleaſure alter and change the Laws of that Kingdom;<note place="margin">Seneca Troas.</note> for as the
<q>Tragaedian—Quodounque libuit facere, victori licet.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which was the perpetual practiſe of the Romans to ſend their <hi>Praetors Proconſuls,</hi> and <hi>Praefects</hi> into thoſe places, which by force and power of Arms they had ſubdued, and to govern them according to their Laws, but <hi>quo Jure,</hi> ſaith <hi>Minius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livy, l. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihil aliud praefecto dicatis, quam armis ſuperatis, vos iis has leges im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pofuiſſe.</hi> Surely you can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but they being overcome by Arms, ye have impoſed thoſe Laws upon them: by which means as by the nerves the <hi>Romans</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned other Nations with them, and made one civil body of them.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108759:30"/>For as <hi>Livy, multitudo cealeſcere in unius populi corpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livy, li. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nulla alia re quam legibus poteſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coke Com. in Littl. fo. <hi>141.</hi>
               </note> a multitude by no other means can grow together in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of one people but by Laws, and as Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> the unity of Laws is the beſt means for the unity of Countries. In which the <hi>Romans</hi> excelled all other Nations, inſomuch as their Laws in their flouriſhing eſtate were almoſt the Laws of all the world. And yet as the Lord <hi>Chauncelor Elſemore</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Poſtnati, fo. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Roman civil Law is taken to be the moſt univerſal and general Law.</hi> Such a deep impreſſion did they make in all Nations who were under the Roman juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>But to come to our Countrey, though ſome Zelots of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws have laboured to clear them from any commixture with the Laws of other Nations, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſeveral conqueſts of the ſame, yet
<q>Vincat amor veri, Vincat amor patriae.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:108759:30"/>
            <p>And the truth is as <hi>Matheus We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtmerienſis</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Britannia</note> 
               <hi>Romani Britanui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am per Julium Caeſarem in latas leges jurare compulſam magna dignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one coluerunt,</hi> and <hi>Camden, Britannis nec legibus ſuis patriis uti permiſſum, ſed magiſtratus a populo Romano cum imperio &amp; ſecuribus miſſi qui jus dicerent.</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> had <hi>Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> in great eſtimation being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> to ſwear to their Laws, neither were they permitted to uſe their Countrey, and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Laws, but Magiſtrates were ſent from the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> with command and authority to make Laws, and command them to be kept, whence came the ſaying of the Ancient Poet quoted by Mr. <hi>Selden.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. fo. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <q>Cernitis ignotos Latia ſub lege Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannos.</q>
            <p>Neither is it a diſparagement to our Laws to have participated of the Laws of other Nations, as ſome ſupoſe, but rather an Elogy for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:108759:31"/>the Roman Laws themſelves were compoſed of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Laws, and as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> though our Laws be mixt as our Language, compounded of <hi>Britan, Saxons Danes, and Normans;</hi> yet did not this add leſſe to them then thoſe who would have them to ſtand out the ſame in all mutations, for no tree is ſo good at the firſt ſett as at tranſplanting. But to proceed,</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe it not altogether imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial to add a fourth inſtrument which the Romans uſed to unite their ſubjected Nations, to wit, the Communication of their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Organ of ſociety by whoſe Communication neceſſary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffairs paſſe between man and man.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And though,<note place="margin">Catil. fo. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Saluſt</hi> ſaith, many of different kind and Languages, convening in one City, <hi>facile coaleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt</hi> may eaſily grow into one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Language; Yet in remote Cities and Nations it fareth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: which moved the Romans to Communicate their language to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108759:31"/>forraign Nations, by rejecting theirs, thereby forcing them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their minds to the knowledge of that without which they could have no comunication, or correſpondence with them, which did very greatly conduce to the Majeſty, utility, and unity of the Roman Commonwealth with other Nations.<note place="margin">Valer. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And therefore as <hi>Valerius</hi> relateth, among other Ceremonies of keeping ſtate, this did they alſo with great perſeverance obſerve, that they ſhould not give any anſwer to the <hi>Graeciaus</hi> but in Latine, and alſo compelled them to ſpeak by an interpreter, not onely in the City of Rome, but alſo in <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Aſia. Quo ſcilicet La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine vecis honos per omnes gentes venerabilior diffunderetur,</hi> By which means alſo the glory of the Latine language ſhould be more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly diffuſed through all Nations: and <hi>Phavorinus</hi> ſaid that an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour might give the freedom of <hi>Rome</hi> to Barbarous Nations, but in Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous words and language he could not, becauſe thoſe things
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108759:32"/>which receive their force and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty from that natural uſage of Citizens, cannot be changed by the authority of the Senate. And in ſuch an eſpecial eſteem had the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans their proper and mother Tongue, that in their publique Aſſemblies, they abſtained from the uſe of Forreign Languages, though they were not ignorant of them:<note place="margin">Suetonius vita Tiber. fo. <hi>216.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Suetonius</hi> writes of <hi>Tiberius</hi> that though he could ſpeak the Greek tongue readily, and fluently, yet he abſtained fro the uſe of it, in the <hi>Senate,</hi> in ſo much, as being about to name the word <hi>Monopolium,</hi> he firſt craved pardon, <hi>quod ſibi pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grino vecabule utendum eſſet,</hi> that he was to uſe an Outlandiſh word. By which means the ſubjugated minds of all Nations began to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbe and faſhion themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the patern, and example of the Romans who were then <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum Domini,</hi> Lords of the world; as the Panegyrical Poet,
<q>
                  <l>—Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitur orbis</l>
                  <l>Regis ad exemplum.<note place="margin">Claud. <hi>4.</hi> Houo.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:108759:32"/>and did not onely ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the obſervance of their laws but alſo to the practice of their Language. For though the <hi>Britains</hi> were, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> acknowledgeth them —<hi>validiſſima gens,</hi> a moſt valiant Nation, and more fierce then the French, and moleſted the Romans with more dangerous Revolts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all Nations the laſt that was conquered, and the firſt were freed; and alſo at the beginning did <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam Romanam abnuere,</hi> reject the Roman language, yet did they at the length,<note place="margin">Vita Agric.</note> 
               <hi>concupiſcere linguam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam, indeque habitus noſtri honor, &amp; frequens toga,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeaks, affect the Roman language, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique, the Roman habit and the like. And ſo deep a tincture and impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did the Roman Language ſtamp &amp; make in theſe occidental parts, that to this day, for the moſt part, they retain an Etymological ſenſe of it, and in our parts of Britany, after the departure of the Romans, we deemed it a glory to draw and expreſs all our writs, declarations,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108759:33"/>and other proceedings in ſuits of Law in the Latine language, until in theſe latter times they were abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted by Acts of Parliament, as a badge of our antient ſervitude; which <hi>Tacitus</hi> himſelf intimateth in theſe words <hi>Itaque humanitas apud imperitos vocabatur cum pars ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and that was called a favour and curteſie by the ignorant, which indeed was a part of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude.</p>
            <p>A fifth may be added though leſſe pertinent, that is the tranſmutation of names, when the victor doth change the name of the conquered Countrey, and calls it by the name of his own Countrey.</p>
            <p>Of which, among the Roman Writers, I find ſome change to be made, but not by the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Emperors. For though ſome of the later Writers, have called all the Nations contained within the Precincts of the Roman Empire, as <hi>Grotius</hi> alledgeth, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grotius l. <hi>2.</hi> fo. <hi>21.</hi> Selden. ib.</note> and <hi>Gildas</hi> ſaith of <hi>Britanny, non Britanuia, ſed Romania cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:108759:33"/>yet no ſuch tranſmutation of names was ever decreed or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> or Edict of the Emperor.<note place="margin">Clapmar de arcan. imperii.</note> For a acute <hi>Clapmar</hi> ſaith, The Romans did little eſteem <hi>talia inania ſimulachra</hi> ſuch vain ſhadows and ſhews, and were not ſollicitous of proud names, ſo that they might have the matter it ſelf. Of which there is an example in the Poet,<note place="margin">Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. <hi>12.</hi> fo. <hi>394.</hi>
               </note> when <hi>Juno</hi> had left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing untried whereby ſhe might impede the Trojans from invading <hi>Italy,</hi> which finding her ſelf unable to effect it, at the laſt defired <hi>Jupiter,</hi> that foraſmuch as the Trojans ſhould poſſeſs and enjoy <hi>Italy,</hi> yet they ſhould not change the name, but the Latins ſhould retain their ancient name.
<q>
                  <l>Ne velis indigenas nomen mutare Latinos,</l>
                  <l>Neu Troas fieri jubeas, Teucroſque vocari:</l>
               </q>
Which <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſmiling to himſelf, caſily condiſcended to, as a matter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108759:34"/>of no moment; for ſo the Poet proceedeth,
<q>
                  <l>Olli ſubridens hominum rerumque repertor,</l>
                  <l>Do quod vis, &amp; me victuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> volenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> remitto.</l>
               </q>
To wind up all in a word; By the premiſes it is perſpicuous, that not only the Britans, but all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which by conqueſt were forced to ſerve under the Roman yoke, were by clemency, and arms, impoſition of laws, and tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Language reduced into one moral and civil body, and were, as it: were, one countrey, and one Commonwealth, inſomuch as by <hi>Modeſtinus</hi> it is called <hi>communit patria,</hi> and by <hi>Claudian, Gens una,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Hujus pacificis debemus moribus omues</l>
                  <l>Quod cuncti gens una ſumus.</l>
               </q>
But now to compare <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Britain,</hi> if it be comely to compare
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108759:34"/>great things with leſſe, which as the Prince of the Roman Poets.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tantum inter alias caput extulit urbes<note place="margin">Virg. Egl. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Quantum lenta ſolent inter viburna cupreſſi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So as, though for largeneſs and extent (it being, as hath been ſaid, <hi>Caput totius orbis,</hi>) it is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet in regard of the quality, and condition of the aboveſaid uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it may admit ſome compariſon; for the conquerours in our <hi>Orbe Britanno,</hi> did follow the tract and ſteps of the Roman conquerours, whereby at the length, upon their conqueſts, they happily arrived at the like ſettlement of the union, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the four diſcordant King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>England, Wales, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, who though he made an abſolute and entire conqueſt of <hi>England,</hi> and might have had all the Lands which he would have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſeized, yet like a Roman
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108759:35"/>clement conquerour he took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mans eſtate from him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baker</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed them of any of their goods but from thoſe whoſe demerit made them unworthy to hold them and would not adhere unto him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the vacancy of Offices, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up the places of thoſe who were ſlain, or fled, was the preſent mean he made for preferring his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and as <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbur</hi> ſaith, in ſubjects <hi>leniter</hi> in rebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>turbide agens foeliciter omit Angl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> potiebatur,</hi> by intreating his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects gently, and the rebels rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, he happily enjoyed all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> For as in the body of a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creature, mature doth convert food and nutriment into good blood and by degrees aſſimilates it to the body;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Fran. Bacon.</note> So in union of countri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by conqueſt, the conquerour ought to expel any part of the ſtate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, which he findeth ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as he cannot convert, and aſſimilate it to the civil body of that ſtate: which was the current courſe of <hi>William</hi> the conquerour. And
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108759:35"/>though ſome Hiſtorians, and Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niclers of thoſe times ſeem to vary from this aſſertion as <hi>Mathew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that after <hi>William</hi> the conquerour had ſubdued the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, <hi>terras Anglorum &amp; poſſeſſiones, apſis expulſis ſucceſſivis manu diſtribuit ſuis commilitonibus,</hi> they being by degrees expelled, he with his hand did diſtribute all the Lands and poſſeſſions of the Engliſh to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militions or fellow ſouldiers, which <hi>Eodin,</hi> and <hi>Ramatus Choppinus</hi> alſo though they had it at the ſecond hand, relate it for truth; yet the contrary is manifeſted by his Act to one <hi>Warren</hi> a <hi>Norman</hi> of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple quality, to whom he had gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Caſtle of <hi>Sherborn</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolk;</hi> But the heir of <hi>Sherborn,</hi> the antient inheritour of that Caſtle, ſhewing to <hi>William</hi> the conquerour that he was his ſubject and leigeman and did inherit the Caſtle by the ſame Law, that the conquerour had allowed, and eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> did therefore pray that he might hold the ſaid Caſtle in peace;<note place="margin">Davys Report. fo: <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108759:36"/>conquerour in this caſe did give judgment for <hi>Sherborn</hi> againſt <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren;</hi> of which judgment <hi>Cambden</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention,<note place="margin">Davys ib.</note> in the diſcription of <hi>Norfolk.</hi> &amp; Juſtice <hi>Calthropp</hi> ſaid that he had ſeen an antient copy of that judgment in the library of Sir <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Heydon</hi> at <hi>Barconſthorp</hi> in <hi>Norfolk;</hi> and as Sir <hi>John Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> reporteth, the contrary appeared by the book of <hi>Doomeſday,</hi> which in this point, is of more credit then all the diſconrſes and chroniclers in the world, wherein is contained an exact diſcription of all the <hi>Realm</hi> made <hi>in the time of the ſaid King, as Henry of Huntington ſetteth forth, per Angliam ita totus regnabat, quol ibi non una hida inerat de qua nu ſciret cujus eſſet,</hi> He ſo totally ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over all England that there was not one hide of Land in it, of which the knew not whoſe it was. By which record it is declared, that he did not take all the lands of the Engliſh into his hands, and confer them on his fellows, for in it is expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what Lands the conquerour ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in demeſne, to wit, the Lands which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108759:36"/>were of St. <hi>Edward,</hi> and are enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Terrae Edwardi Regis,</hi> and others which himſelf had ſeiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conqueſt, and were entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Terrae Regis,</hi> without ſaying any more, as is noted 49. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.23. a And thoſe Lands are now called the antient demeſne Lands of the King, or of the Crown of England, and in this book, the poſſeſſions of other Lands are put in certain, as well as the poſſeſſions of the King, and thoſe Lands which are under other titles, as <hi>Terrae Epiſcopi de Exeter,</hi> &amp;c. And all other Lands which were in others hands and named in that book, are frank free, 40. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.45. <hi>Fitz. N. B.</hi> 16. O. And alſo Roman like what he had purchaſed with his ſword, he poſſeſſed by his ſword: For as Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cok. pref. l. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to ejus Regiminis tempore, aut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictus nunquam interquievit gladius, aut perpetuo manus inſtitit capulo iterato evaginatura.</hi> In all the time of his raign his drawn ſword never reſted, or otherwiſe his hand was alwaies on his hilt ready to draw it
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108759:37"/>again, and at the firſt, had no other way to make his victory permanent but by his valour.</p>
            <p>But after the <hi>Norman</hi> conqueror had brought under his yoke and ſubjection, the utmoſt parts of this <hi>Iſland,</hi> and by his continual victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries tamed the minds of his formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable enemies; he like a Roman victor, with all diligence laboured by impoſition of Laws to reduce the Engliſh and the <hi>Normans</hi> into a peaceable and ſociable uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and accordingly propounded to himſelf an exact ſurvey of all the antient Laws, as the old Laws of the Saxons, which where compounded of the Britiſh cuſtoms and their own which mention the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Law, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nellage,</hi> the <hi>Mercian</hi> Law, <hi>Mercem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage,</hi> and the <hi>Weſt Saxon, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaxonlage:</hi> All theſe being conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>William</hi> the conquerour, comparing them with the Laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Norway,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> which he moſt affected, as Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> ſuppoſeth, becauſe by them a Baſtard of a Concubine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf was, had equal inheritance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108759:37"/>with the moſt legitimate ſon, as <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> of <hi>Tilbury<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in this dialogue <hi>de Seaccario</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quaſdam reprobarit, quaſdam autem approbans, illis, tranſmarinas Neuſtriae leges quae ad regni pacem tuendam efficaciſſimae videbantur, addidit,</hi> ſome he rejected and ſome he approving, to them he added the forraign <hi>Norway</hi> Laws, which ſeemed moſt efficacious for the preſerving of the peace of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And ſuch laws as he in writing allowed, though by <hi>Roger Hovendon</hi> and <hi>Iugulphus</hi> they were called <hi>Leges Edwardi regis,</hi> yet by <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> are they properly called, <hi>Bonae, &amp; approbatae antiquae regui leges,</hi> the good and approved antient Laws of the Kingdom by denomination from the greater part. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Laws and cuſtoms of King <hi>William.</hi> For clearly diverſe <hi>Norman</hi> cuſtoms were in practiſe firſt mixt with them, and to theſe times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, as Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> aſſerteth, as that of <hi>Coverfeu</hi> which was conſtituted to prevent conſpiracies, combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and robberies, which were then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108759:38"/>very frequent, and commonly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and practiſed in the night. And therefore it was ordained that in all townes and villages a bell ſhould be rung at eight of the Clock in the evening, and that in every houſe they ſhould then put out their fire, and lights (which bell was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Coverfeu</hi>) and then to go to bed, which, among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was one of the laws much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the preſervation of peace. By which ſo great a peace was ſetled in the Kingdom, as by <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Huntington</hi> he is ſtiled the Author of peace; whoſe words are theſe, <hi>Pacis author tantus, quod puella auro onuſta regnum Angliae tranſire poſſit impune.</hi> He was ſo great an Author of peace, that a Virgin laden with gold, might without danger paſſe through the Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing his people to be part Normans,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon.</hi> uſes of the law <hi>fol.</hi> 31.</note> and part Saxons, the Normans he brought with him, the Saxons he found here; he bent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to conjoin them by marriages in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108759:38"/>amity; and for that purpoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, that if thoſe of his Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen, ſhould die leaving their Heir within age, a Male within one and twenty, and a Female within fourteen years, and unmarried, then the King ſhould have the beſtowing of ſuch in ſuch a Family, and to ſuch perſons as he ſhould think meet, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to his Normans, which inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of marriage went ſtill imployed, and doth continue at this day in every tenure, is called Knights ſervice.</p>
            <p>Then he alſo commanded all his laws to be written in French, and all cauſes, and matters of law to be proſecuted, pleaded and diſpatched in the French language (as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans did in Latin) that the Engliſh thereby, might be invited to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict their minds to the knowledge of that Language. That whereas they were made by Laws, as it were one people, ſo by this conſtitution they might be brought to be of one Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. In this manner (through the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108759:39"/>proweſs and prudence of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Conquerour) were the Engliſh and the Normans ſo entirely united that they ſeemed one Nation and one people without any difference or diſtinction of reſpect and honour, as <hi>Dido</hi> promiſed the <hi>Trojans,</hi>
               <q>Tros, Tyriuſque mihi nullo diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine agetur.</q> Which may more effectually be applied to him; for he and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny reigned over them ſo united, for the ſpace of five hundred years.</p>
            <p>The next bordering Principality to <hi>England</hi> is <hi>Wales,</hi> and therefore firſt in order by the Engliſh to be conquered, according to the Roman Example, as indeed it was. A ſtout and hardy Nation <hi>Bellicoſiſſima gens,</hi> as <hi>Cambden,</hi> and indeed the reliques of the auntient Britans, who becauſe they would not ſubject themſelues to the Tyranny of the <hi>Saxous</hi> (as the other Engliſh did) were forced by their armes to retreat
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108759:39"/>into the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Region of that <hi>Iſland</hi> for refuge, ſurrounded with the muniments of nature as moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and armes of the Sea, which antiently was called <hi>Cambria,</hi> as the people at this preſent <hi>Cambro-Britauni.</hi> In ſo much as the <hi>Saxons</hi> were unable by their force to make way unto them, and to overcome them. And though by ſome of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, a ditch of a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full work was framed, which was called King <hi>Offa</hi> his ditch, by which they divided that Country from England, and called them Walsh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that is to ſay unto them ſtrangers, yet did they continually with fire and ſword, ſpoile and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populate their fieldes and Cities. And when the <hi>Heptarchy</hi> of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xons</hi> was devolved into a Monarchy could they onely by <hi>Athelſtane</hi> (that victorious King) be made tributary; nay <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> (the terror of his time) <hi>Cujus nomen</hi> (as <hi>William of Weſtminſter</hi>) <hi>exterae &amp; remotae gentes timebant,</hi> whoſe ruine and downfall the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108759:40"/>Welch alſo conſpired, And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the ſaid <hi>William</hi> ſaith, though he raiſed a Copious army againſt the <hi>Welch</hi> with an intention to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them to his ſword, as he had done the Engliſh, yet did he me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with ſuch martiall reſiſtance, that he was content to accept of their homage with faithfull hoſtages to pay him tribute, though after upon their reſtleſs commotions he placed divers of his Norman Nobility upon the confines towards <hi>Wales,</hi> and gave a power unto the perſons thus placed, to make ſuch conqueſts on the Welch, as they by their own ſtrength could accompliſh, whereby divers of thoſe parts were won by the Sword from the Welchmen, which were planted with Engliſh Colonies, and called Barons Marches. Which though his Son <hi>William Rufus</hi> ſeconded, yet was it a great glory for him only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the Shire of <hi>Pembroke</hi> which was a very ancient Shire of <hi>Wales;</hi> ſo as this parcel of this Iſland called <hi>Wales,</hi> was no parcel of the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:108759:40"/>of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> but was diſtinguiſhed from the ſame, and was, as it were, a Realm of it ſelf, not governed by the laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ployd Com. <hi>192.</hi>
               </note> as the Books of the laws of this Realm do teſtifie: yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs afterwards was the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Wales</hi> holden in chief, and in Fee of the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Prince thereof being then of their own Nation was compellable upon Summons to appeare in the Parliament of England to do this homage. And eſcuage was firſt invented for them, and the Scots, as <hi>Ployden</hi> ſaith, againſt whom War was made by the Kings of England as rebels, not as enemies, for that they were ſubject to England, and were within the Sea. And ſo thoſe of Wales were ſubject to the King of England,<note place="margin">Vide Ploid. fol. <hi>129.</hi> B.</note> though they were not parcel of the body of the Realm of England. And hence was it that <hi>Henry</hi> the third upon the often revolts of the Welch endeavoured to aſſume the territory of <hi>Wales,</hi> as forfeited, to himſelf,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108759:41"/>and conferred the ſame upon <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Longſhank, his Heir-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, who took upon him the name of Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> yet could not obtain the poſſeſſion, or any profit thereby, for the former Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> continued his government, for which cauſe between him and the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> Wars did rage; whereof the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to King <hi>Henry</hi> his Father,<note place="margin">An. <hi>1257.</hi> fol. <hi>914.</hi>
               </note> who made him this anſwer, as <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> reciteth it, <hi>Quid ad me tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> terra? ex dono meo eſt. Exerce vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res primitivas, famam excita juveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, &amp; de caetero timeant inimici,</hi> &amp;c. What is your territory to me? it is of my gift. Advance your primitive for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſtir up your juvenile renown, and as for the reſidue, let your enemies fear you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Fathers Heroical incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, he fortunately enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for as the <hi>Comaedian</hi> to that purpoſe.
<q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quiſque filium ſuum vult eſſe,<note place="margin">Terent.</note> ita eſt.</q>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:108759:41"/>And not long after, ſundry Battails were fought between the ſaid <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> both before and after he was King of England with <hi>Leolan</hi> the laſt Prince of the Welch blood, and <hi>David</hi> his brother, until both the ſaid Prince, and his ſaid Brother were overcome by the ſaid <hi>Edward,</hi> after he was King of England, who thereby firſt made a conqueſt of <hi>Wales</hi> and afterwards annexed it to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The territory of <hi>Wales</hi> being thus united, the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> uſed means to obtain the peoples good will, thereby to ſtrengthen that which he had gotten by effuſion of blood, with the good will and affection of his ſubjects: who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed their moſt harty and humble obedience, if it would pleaſe the King to remain among them himſelf in perſon, or elſe to appoint over them a governour that was of their own Nation, and Countrey.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the cunning King projecteth a pretty policy, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Queen (being then great
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108759:42"/>with child) into <hi>Wales,</hi> where ſhe was delivered of a Son, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Carnarvon.</hi> The King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent for all the Barons of <hi>Wales,</hi> and remembred them of their ſubmiſs aſſurance tendred according to their former proffers, if they ſhould have a governour of their own countrey, and who could not ſpeak one word of Engliſh, whoſe life and converſation no man was able to ſtain or blemiſh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired their offered obedience: whereunto they yeilding, the King preſented unto them his ſaid Son born at <hi>Carnarvon</hi> Caſtle, whom thereupon the Barons unanimouſly embraced for their Prince, and afterwards made their homage to him at <hi>Creſter. Anno.</hi> 29. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. as Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> And though the Welch Nation do not willingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the aforeſaid conqueſt, but refer it rather to this compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet as Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt made a conqueſt of the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Davys vep. fol. <hi>41.</hi> B.</note> as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in his charter, or ſtatute of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108759:42"/>
               <hi>Rutland,</hi> where it is ſaid <hi>Divina providentia terram Walliae cum inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſuis prius nobis jure feodali ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam, in proprietatis noſtrae dominium convertit, &amp; coronae Regis noſtri an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thereupon according to the courſe and power of conquerours, as the ſame Author ſaith, he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their Laws and cuſtoms as it is alſo expreſſed in the ſaid charter, or ſtatute. For as to the Laws and cuſtoms he ſaith. <hi>Quaſdam illarum de concilio procerum regni noſtri de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levimus, Quaſdam correximus, etiam quaſdam alias adjiciendas, &amp; faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end as decrevimus,</hi> &amp;c. Some of them by the council of the Peers of our Realm have we expunged, ſome have we corrected, and alſo ſome have we determined to be made and added, and as another ſaith, divided ſome parts thereof into ſhires, and appointed Laws for the government of that people.</p>
            <p>Yet though the King had gained the property of that Kingdom, and that the Inhabitants of it, <hi>de
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108759:43"/>Alto &amp; Baſso,</hi> as it is recited in the ſaid charter, had ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his will: yet it appears, that he did admit all thoſe who would be ruled and governed by the common Law of England, which he had eſtabliſhed among them, by the ſaid charter, to have Frank Tenement and Inheritance in their Lands; for there he preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth a form of the writ <hi>de Aſſize de novel diſſeiſin, de mort Daunca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp; de dower</hi> to be brought of Lands in <hi>Wales</hi> according to the courſe of the common Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and when they wanted a writ of form to ſupply the preſent caſe, they uſed the writ <hi>Quod ei deforceat</hi> 2. E. 4.12. <hi>A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was the Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> united to the crown of <hi>England</hi> by the valour and wiſdome of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and the principality of it hath conſtantly ſince appertained to the Eldeſt Sons of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ployd. Com. fol. <hi>126.</hi> B.</note> as <hi>Ployden</hi> ſaith, from all time that there hath been a Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> or as Sir <hi>John Doderidge,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:108759:43"/>to the eldeſt Son or the next ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Heir. For <hi>Henry</hi> the third firſt made <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his eldeſt Son Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> and gave to him the Dominion and dignity of it, and alſo <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond after he was King of <hi>England</hi> created <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third in his life time Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> and the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> eldeſt Danghter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight,<note place="margin">Doderidge <hi>principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of</hi> Wales fol. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> and afterwards Queen of <hi>England</hi> did carry the title of Princeſs of <hi>Wales.</hi> Et <hi>Sic de Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding this conqueſt by <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt and general ſubmiſſion of the Welch, were there divers inſurrections fomented by them againſt the former eſtabliſhed Government, and eſpecially one which happened in his Raign raiſed by <hi>Rice up Meredick</hi> who rebelled againſt the King, upon which all the lands of the ſaid <hi>Meredick</hi> were confiſcated, as forfeited, and ſeiſed by the ſaid King,<note place="margin">Doderidge <hi>Prince of</hi> Wales, fol. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> and nominally given by his ſucceſſour <hi>Edward</hi> the third, to <hi>Edward</hi> the black Prince,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108759:44"/>Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> for his better main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and honourable ſupport; and though after the death of the Father they aſſiſted <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond his ſon in his Wars againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herbert. Hen. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and got victories for <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and ſtood firm, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the differences in this realm, to his Grandchild <hi>Richard</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: yet when the unfortunate, and fatal Wars happened between the two Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> the Welchmen fell from their fidelity to the Crown, hoping upon that diſaſterous mutation to regain their priſtine liberty. For as Sir <hi>John Baker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>of</hi> England fol. <hi>139.</hi>
               </note> It was always a cuſtom with that Nation at every change of the Princes of <hi>England</hi> to try concluſions, hoping at one time or another to have a day of it, and to change their yoke of bondage into Liberty; as upon the aforeſaid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity they began to lift up their hands and heads, and under the aſpiring command of <hi>Owen Glendoer</hi> waged a terrible War with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who through the combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108759:44"/>and confederacy of the Earl of <hi>March,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Firrcy</hi> ſwallowed in his ambitious mind all <hi>Wales</hi> and the Lands beyond <hi>Severn</hi> Weſtwards, which were aſſigned to him for his part; but the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a skilful ſould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, having orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and diſpoſed his Army, ſuddenly marched towards the Lords, having a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſpecial care that they ſhould by no means join with the Welch; and ſo encountering the Lords ſingly, obteined an univerſal victory; and the Welch thereupon abandoned <hi>Owen Glendoer,</hi> who hirking in the Woods was there famiſhed. And after the Fate of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth his ſon knowing the faſhion of the Welch;<note place="margin">Bakers <hi>Hiſt.</hi> f. <hi>241</hi>
               </note> that in time of change they would commonly cake advantage to make Inroads upon the borders cauſed forts and bulwarks in fit places to be erected, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Garriſons in them for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, or repelling any ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions; yet ſo prompt and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous were they continually upon the leaſt opportunity to ſuch inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108759:45"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t nullo modo induci potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> (as <hi>Cambden</hi> ſaith) <hi>ut ſervitutis jugum ſubirent, nec ulla ratione res componi, &amp; Funeſtiſſimum inter gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes odium reſtingui potuit, donec</hi> Henricus 7. <hi>ab illis oriundus ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem manum jacentibus Britannis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexerit, &amp;</hi> Henr. 8. <hi>eos in parem juris libertatiſque conditionem atque nos ipſi Angli ſumus acceperit;</hi> that by no means they could be induced to undergo the yoke of ſervitude, neither by any reaſon could matten be compounded, and the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mortal hatred between thoſe two Nations be extinguiſhed, until <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh deſcended of them had extended his ſoveraign hand to the forlorn Britans, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight had received them into the equal condition of right and liberty, even as we Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen are. And indeed <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> the Seventh was deſcended of <hi>Owen Tuder,</hi> who is ſaid to be deſcended of <hi>Cadwallader</hi> a Prince of <hi>Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (wherein the Welch prophecy ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them now to be fulfilled, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:108759:45"/>one of the Princes of <hi>Wales</hi> ſhould be Crowned with the Diadem of <hi>Brute,</hi> which Prince <hi>Leolin</hi> before vainly aferibed unto himſelf) who therefore was chearfully aſſiſted by the Welchmen to the title of the Crown,<note place="margin">Herbert. <hi>H. 8.</hi> f. <hi>369</hi>
               </note> they being deſirous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opoſition made by them to <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt to have a Prince of their own Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to rule over them.</p>
            <p>Yet were not the Welchmen fully ſatisfied with this union, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a more entire union by laws; for notwithſtanding the Laws which were eſtabliſhed in that Country by <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. there were 141 Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of Marchers, which were then neither any part of <hi>Wales</hi> though formerly conquered out of <hi>Wales,</hi> neither any part of that Shire of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, who by the licenſe of the Kings then Reigning,<note place="margin">Davis cep. f. <hi>61. B.</hi>
               </note> had Royall ſigniories in their ſeveralter itories. 9. <hi>H.</hi> 6.12. 152. &amp; 11. <hi>H.</hi> 4.40. and a kind of Palatine juriſdiction and a power to adminiſter Juſtice to their tenants in every of their
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108759:46"/>territories, revoking their own Laws and cuſtoms at their pleaſure, that the writs of ordinary juſtice out of the Kings court were not for the moſt part current among them, and ſubſtituted Officers at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,<note place="margin">Herb. H. <hi>8.</hi> fo. <hi>369.</hi>
               </note> who practiſed ſtrange and diſcrepant cuſtoms, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch rapins that nothing was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſafe nor quiet in thoſe parts; for by reaſon of the flight of the offendors from one Lordſhip to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother they had eſcaped due and condign puniſhment: whereupon the nobleſt and eldeſt of that Nation ſupplicating <hi>Henry</hi> the eight,<note place="margin">Herb. ibid.</note> did crave to be received and adopted into the ſame Laws and priviledges which his other ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> enjoyed, which moved the King to make the ſtatute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 26. by which is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enacted, that the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> ſhall be incorporated, united, and annexed to the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> altering in many parts the former juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Government thereof,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108759:46"/>bringing the ſame to the like admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of juſtice, as was and yet is uſual in <hi>England,</hi> appointing that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> ſhould take place there, and all Welch Laws, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter cuſtoms and tenures not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the laws of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be thenceforth ever abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and aboliſhed: and therefore whereas before there had been eight ſeveral Shires in <hi>Wales,</hi> beſides the County of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and that ſome other territories in <hi>Wales</hi> were then no Shire grounds, by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the laws of <hi>England</hi> could have no currant paſſage therein; by the ſaid Act there were erected in <hi>Wales</hi> four other, namely the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Shires of <hi>Radnor, Brecknock, Mountgomery,</hi> and <hi>Denbigh,</hi> by which means the Laws of <hi>England</hi> there alſo might be put into execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion And further the ſaid Lord <hi>Marchers</hi> grounds by the ſame Act were annexed and united, partly to the Shires of <hi>England,</hi> and partly to the Shires of <hi>Wales</hi> next adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as thought then by reaſon of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108759:47"/>vicinity of the place and otherwiſe moſt convenient to prevent the perpretating of the aforeſaid enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and odious offences by juſt and lawful puniſhments.</p>
            <p>And to make the Union the more honourable, and that the nobleſt of the Welch Nation might partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the higheſt priviledges and chiefeſt dignities of <hi>England,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Roman precedent, it was alſo ordained that out of the ſaid Shires of <hi>Wales</hi> there ſhould be one Knight, and out of every of the Shire Towns in <hi>Wales</hi> named in the ſaid Act there be one Burgeſſe elected after the Engliſh manner; which Knights and Burgeſſes ſo ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and duely upon ſummons of every Parliament in <hi>England</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, ſhould have place and voice. in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as other the Burgeſſes and Knights of <hi>England</hi> uſed to have.</p>
            <p>And though the ſaid ſtatute doth not make mention of the penalty given upon the Sheriffs falſe return for ſuch Knights and Burgeſſes as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108759:47"/>ſhall be lawfully elected in <hi>Wales,</hi> and not returned, but that thoſe were given by the ſtatute of 23. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 15. againſt the Sheriffs of <hi>England;</hi> yet ſhall the Knights and Burgeſſes of <hi>Wales</hi> ſo elected and not returned, have the benefit of it by the ſtatute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. becauſe that ſtatute grants that the Countrey of <hi>Wales</hi> ſhall have, enjoy, &amp; inherit all rights, priviledges &amp; laws within it's Dominions, as other ſubjects of the King born in this Realm: for the general words of the ſtatute make all the laws of <hi>England</hi> aſwel Common laws as Statute laws to be of effect in <hi>Wales,</hi> and ſhall take place there, and that the Welchmen ſhall have the benefic of the Engliſh laws for things done in <hi>Wales,</hi> as the Engliſh ſhall have for things done in <hi>England,</hi> and by a <hi>Quodei deforceat</hi> the Welch ſhall take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntage of all actions real aſwel given by the common law as the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Realm, <hi>Vide Com. Ployd. Beckleys</hi> caſe <hi>Fo.</hi> 128. <hi>Fo.</hi> 129. and befides becauſe the Welch uſe a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108759:48"/>ſpeech nothing like or conſonant to the Mother tongue uſed within this Realm, &amp; that ſome rude and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people did make a diſtinction and diverſity between the ſubjects of this Realm, and the ſubjects of the other, whereby great diviſion &amp; vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance did grow between the ſaid peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as in the preamble of the ſaid act is expreſſed; therefore more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally toconjoyn thoſe diſſonant Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as well by Language, as by Laws, it was alſo by that ſtatute ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that none that uſe the Welch Language ſhall enjoy any office or fees within the Kings Dominions, but ſhall forfeit them, unles they uſe the Engliſh Language; by which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception the Welchmen (who before much gloried in the Antiquity and ſimplicity of their <hi>Britiſh</hi> Language) were ſtirred on to bend their ſtudy and practice to the knowledge and pronunciation of the Engliſh Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; To the propriety of which moſt of them within few years at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and at this day generally affect, and uſe it with delight, which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:108759:48"/>hath been an inſtrumental means of a more amicable union between theſe two Nations. And for the execution of the laws, it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the County of Monmouth formerly being a ſhire of <hi>Wales</hi> ſhould be governed from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in like manner, &amp; by the ſame ludges as other ſhires of England were: And for the other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> elue ſhires a ſpeciall Iuriſdiction and Officers were ordained, yet in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance agreeable after the manner of the Engliſh laws. And finally, by that Statute, Gavelkind and all other ſiniſter cuſtomes of <hi>Wales</hi> were aboliſhed, but all cuſtomes which are reaſonable and agreeable to any cuſtomes of <hi>England</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. For by the ſame Statute it is provided, that a Commiſſion ſhall iſſue to examine the Welch cuſtoms, and that thoſe that ſhall be found reaſonable, upon a Certificate of the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall be allowed, <hi>Davis Rep. f.</hi> 40. And accordingly whereas there was a Cuſtome in <hi>Denbigh,</hi> that a Feme Covert
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:108759:49"/>with her husband might alien land by ſurrender, and examination in Court: <hi>Wray</hi> and <hi>Dyer</hi> were of opinion, that it ſhall bind the feme, and heirs of the feme as a fine, though th feme after iſſue make ſuch an alienation, and die; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there given why the cuſtome is not taken away, is for that it is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and agreeable to ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms in <hi>England,</hi> for the aſſurance of purchaſers; for the title of the Act is for Laws and Juſtice to be miniſtred in like form as in this Realm, <hi>Vide Dyer,</hi> 363. <hi>pl.</hi> 26. In like manner was it holden, 19. <hi>Eliz. Dyer. f.</hi> 345. <hi>pl.</hi> 13. that whereas before the ſubjection of <hi>Wales</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> a man did hold lands of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> by ſervice to go in his War; it was no tenure of which the Common Law might take notice, for the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality of <hi>Wales</hi> was not governed by the Common law, but was a Dominion of it ſelf, and had their proper laws and cuſtoms: and for that reaſon when that Countrey was
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108759:49"/>reduced under the ſubjection of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch tenure as was of the perſon of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> could not become a <hi>Capite</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enure of the King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this manner and by the means of the ſaid Act of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. were the Welch Nation, and the Engliſh more entirely united by lows then before; of which union enſued a greater peace, tranquility and civility, and infinite good to the inhabitants of the Countrey of <hi>Wales,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued during the Reign of Six ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Kings and Queens, until the horrid and irreconcileable War broke out between the King and Parliament, wherein the Welch upon changes, being always Changelings, in the beginning levied Forces in Defence of the Parliament againſt the KING; in which War though a proſperous event ſucceeded, the royal Brigades being totally van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, and the King himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the Army, yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed they unto themſelves their ancient animoſity; and being
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108759:50"/>poſſeſſed with a conceit that they were never conquered, but by compoſition; now adventured once more to make trial of their Brittiſh valour under the Commiſſion of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Major General <hi>Rowland Laughorn,</hi> Colonel <hi>Rice Powel</hi> and Colonel <hi>John Poyer,</hi> who before had been Commanders for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and in a warlike and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile manner poſſeſſed themſelves of divers Garriſons and Towns againſt the Parliament; and <hi>Laughorn</hi> being a General of great eſteem in thoſe parts, raiſed an Army, which in a ſmall time increaſed to the number of 8000 Horſe and Foot: which by Colonel <hi>Horton</hi> (who was ſent by the Parliament to ſuppreſs that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection) through the aſſiſtance of the Almighty was totally routed, a great ſlaughter committed, and three thouſand priſoners taken, with all their ammunition. A happy Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Parliament; their Forces conſiſting meerly of three Thouſand men; and a diſaſterous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108759:50"/>for the Welch; who nevertheleſs perſiſted in their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. For <hi>Laughorn</hi> and <hi>Powel</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaping by flight got to <hi>Poyer</hi> into <hi>lembroke</hi> Caſtle, who before kept that ſtrong Hold for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and now having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified it with a company of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, with great courage main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it againſt them: ſo great was the danger, and difficult the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, that Lieutenant General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> himſelf, was ſent with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments into <hi>Wales</hi> to impede the Welch as well from rallying &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting their fugitive and diſperſed Forces, as to diſpoſſeſs them of the Towns, Garriſons, and Caſtles, they had treacherouſly ſurpriſed: who firſt reſolved to beſiage <hi>Chepſtow</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but haſtning to <hi>Pembrook</hi> which was more conſiderable, he left Colonel <hi>Eure</hi> there, who within fifteen days took that Caſtle, and ſlew <hi>Kemiſh</hi> to whom before it had been betrayed. But <hi>Pembroke</hi> Caſtle was not ſo facile to be vanquiſhed, and by <hi>Poyer</hi> deemed impregnable,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:108759:51"/>who relying on the ſtrength of the place refuſed all conditions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Cromwell</hi> not enduring the repulſe with an aſſured confidence beſieged it, and through the accommodation of Sir <hi>Ceorge Aſcue,</hi> who furniſhed him with great Guns from the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and all things neceſſary for a ſiege forced <hi>Foyer,</hi> and <hi>Laug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn</hi> at the laſt being brought to extremiſt, (though it had been long ſtouth maintained by them,) to ſurrender and deliver up the Caſtle without conditions, rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing themſelves priſoners at mercy, for which deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries by order of Parliaments publick thanksgiving to God was Solemnized.</p>
            <p>And why ſhould I now expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the queſtion with the Welch whether they ever were conquered by the Engliſh, when as now the beſt and moſt knowing of them have ingeniouſly acknowledged that they were never conquered before.
<q>Jamque habemus Confitentes victos.</q>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:108759:51"/>
But what may ſeem to be the cauſe why the inſurrections of the Welch were ſo frequent, but that <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt contrary to the Roman Garbe upon his firſt conqueſt did admit all of them to the poſſeſſion and inheritance of their Lands and goods, which would be ruled and governed by the common law of <hi>England,</hi> and did forbear to ſettle a Militia, or deduce Colonies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, thereby to reſtrain them from future Commotions: which the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> prudently obſerving were induced to put in practiſe the old Roman rule.
<q>Parcere ſubjeciis, &amp; debellare ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbos.</q>
And ordained that all perſons whatſoever that were in actual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the ſaid inſurrections, and all other perſons that have willingly by council or force aſſiſted the ſame, or contributed any money's, horſe or armes, amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition, or other aid
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:108759:52"/>or aſſiſtance thereof are adjudged delinquents, and that their eſtates be ſequeſtred, and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners named and appointed in the ſaid ordinance or ſuch perſons as they ſhall appoint, do ſeize the eſtates real and perſonal of all and every the ſaid perſons, delinquents aforeſaid, and alſo to make ſale, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and diſpoſe of all and every the Goods, Chattels, Debts, Rents, and perſonal eſtates of all and every the ſaid Delinquents, and let, ſet, and improve their Lands at the beſt rate they can, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of ſequeſtration <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on ſome of their Ieaders did they inflict capical puniſhment, therein alſo purſuing the juſtice of the antient Roman Empire,<note place="margin">Grot. de J. B. &amp; P. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui de captis hoſtium civibus vindictam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſumebant,</hi> who did take revenge of the Captains of their enemies which were taken, by death, for which <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> the Son of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Panegyrick.</p>
            <p>And further for the ſecuring of the Parliament, and mutual defence
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108759:52"/>and ſafety of each other, did they ſettle and conſtitute the Militia in thoſe parts, which had a reſemblance of the Roman Colonies: and at this preſent are there military Garriſons continued in the chiefeſt Cities of <hi>Wales,</hi> by which means ever ſince that countrey hath been kept and maintained in peace and tranquility without the ſuſpicion of any inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and a conſtant unity ſetled between theſe two Nations.</p>
            <p>The conqueſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it's vicinity with <hi>England</hi> is in the next place to be conſidered, and eſpecially for that deadly feud and perpetual wars have time out of mind raged between theſe two Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nam rara eſt inter eos pax dum illi propagari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Brit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fol. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hi retinere imperium ſtudent:</hi> for peace was rare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them while they endeavoured to propagate their Empire and theſe to retein it; which though the Engliſh for many Ages with all their skill and force have contended to vanquiſh, yet could they not until
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108759:53"/>theſe latter times accompliſh. So difficult a task it was to conquer that valiant Nation, and by force to bring it to an union; for as the ſame Author ſaith, <hi>Eadem utriſque in bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ferocia.</hi> And as an other, <hi>Gens virorum fortium fuit quam frugum feracior,</hi> It was a countrey more abounding in proper men then in goodly fruits. A fierce Nation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, which was never ſubjugated by the Romans; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> who lived in the ſecond Age according to the Chriſtian computation inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth,<note place="margin">Apolog.</note> ſaying: <hi>Evangelium diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt in omnes orbis partes, etiam in Britanniam uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Inſulae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Romanae vires nunquam penetrarunt,</hi> The Goſpel was diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through all the parts of the world, alſo into Britany, and even into that part of the Iſland which the Romans never pierced, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that part of the Iſland which is now called <hi>Scotland;</hi> But the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans attempting it, were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rebutted and repulſed by them; and in fine were foreed to frame
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:108759:53"/>walls, trenches and bulwarks, to defend their Province from their terrible incurſions, which were firſt built by <hi>Adrian,</hi> as <hi>Aelius Spartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> then by <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> as <hi>Julius Capitolinus;</hi> and thirdly by <hi>Severus,</hi> thereby to ſtop the furious invaſions of the <hi>Scots,</hi> of which <hi>Claudian</hi> doth mention.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Venit &amp; extremis legio praetentae Britannis</l>
               <l>Quae Scoto dat fraena truci.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But whereas <hi>Buchanan</hi> a partial Trumpeter of his countrey praiſes,<note place="margin">De jure regni apud <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </note> ſaith; <hi>Nos regnum exiguum quidem, ſed jam bis mille annos ab exterar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m gentium imperio liberum tenemus;</hi> we hold our Kingdom, a little one indeed, but now for the ſpace of two thouſand years free from the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of forreign Nations: yet to the contrary ſaith <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, Quod Reges Angliae Jure Superioris &amp; directi Dominii, ab anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſſimis temporibus regno</hi> Scotiae <hi>&amp; ipſius regibus praefuerunt, &amp; ab ipſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:108759:54"/>&amp; illorum pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceribus regalia homagia receperunt &amp; fidelitatis debita jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta,</hi> that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> by the right of a more ſuperior &amp; direct Dominion, from the moſt ancient times had their preheminence over the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> and their Kings, and have received legall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages from them and their Nobles, and due Oaths of fidelity. For after the <hi>Saxons</hi> had made a Conqueſt of the <hi>Britans,</hi> and reduced their Heptarchy into a Monarchy, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it's name into <hi>England; Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the power of their victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Armes,<note place="margin">Holling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Ed. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> was compelled to do homage and fealty to <hi>England,</hi> and to be tributary to their ſueceeding Kings for <hi>Edward</hi> the ſon of <hi>Alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad it under his Dominion;<note place="margin">Herb. Hen. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Athelſtane</hi> made one <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> King thereof, <hi>Eldreck</hi> took ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Ericus,</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> of <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulph,</hi> Kings of <hi>Scots, Malcome</hi> did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to <hi>Knuto,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the confeſſor gave the Kingdom to <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,</hi> who did homage to <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour and to <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:108759:54"/>and <hi>Edgar</hi> did homage to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the firſt, and <hi>David</hi> did homage to <hi>Matilda</hi> the Empreſs, which were without intermiſſion tranſacted by the ſucceeding Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the ſucceeding Kings of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herb. ib.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth: which incited <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth to claim homage and fealty of <hi>James</hi> the fourth, which was partly the cauſe of the quarrel and famous Battail between him and the King, ſo as the aforeſaid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages &amp; fealties made by the Kings of <hi>Scots</hi> were not only for the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Huntington</hi> as the <hi>Scots</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. For <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving married the Daughter and Heir of the Earl of <hi>Huntington</hi> and <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and received the inveſtiture thereof, did not onely do homage and owe fealty for the Earldom of <hi>Huntington,</hi> as alſo his ſon <hi>Malcome</hi> did; but the ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did alſo homage and made fealty for the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>Matilda</hi> the Empreſs; as alſo all the ſucceeding Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:108759:55"/>did, according to the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p>But of all the Kings of <hi>England</hi> none equalled <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and none as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> ſaith, is more celebrated with the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of War and Wiſedome, and eſpecially for his purpoſe and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe for the conqueſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> bending his mind not to glorious conqueſts abroad, but to the ſetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by conqueſt of a ſolid union between thoſe two diſcordant Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as before he had done between <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> For which his heroick Acts the Fame of his vertue ſo wrought on the minds of the <hi>Scots,</hi> that great contention intervening between them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſucceſſion to the crown, <hi>Alexander</hi> the King of <hi>Scots</hi> leaving no Heir, there being twelve com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors,<note place="margin">Holling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> who by ſeveral titles laid claim unto the crown: all of them referred the deciſion of that royal caſe, without any conſtraint, and of their own good will, (as in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is expreſſed) to the final ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, who after
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108759:55"/>ſix years diſcuſſion adjudged the caſe on <hi>Baliols</hi> ſide; who indeed had the beſt title, but upon promiſe to ſubject the crown of <hi>Scotland</hi> to him, and to ſwear fealty and homage to him as his ſovereign Lord; and thereupon is <hi>Baliol</hi> crowned King of <hi>Scotland:</hi> which being done, King <hi>Baliol</hi> comes to <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> where King <hi>Edward</hi> then lay, and there with the chief of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility did ſwear fealty, and do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to him as their ſovereign Lord, except <hi>Bruce</hi> who was the next Heir to the crown.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> thus became the ſovereign Umpire and ſupreme Judge of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to whom the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles as the King himſelf before had done, appealed for Juſtice againſt the King. And becauſe King <hi>Edward</hi> would not permit King <hi>Baliol</hi> a Procurator, but cauſed him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his cauſe himſelf in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary place, in a rage at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, he defyeth King <hi>Edward,</hi> renounceth his allegiance as illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made without the Conſent of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:108759:56"/>States.<note place="margin">Holling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> For which King <hi>Balioll</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſummoned to appeare at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> and refuſing to come, King <hi>Edward,</hi> triumphantly with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty army invaded <hi>Scotland: Barwick</hi> is firſt taken, and afterwards the Caſtles of <hi>Dunbar, Roxborrough, Edinborrough, Sterling,</hi> and <hi>St. Johns;</hi> and <hi>John Warren Earle</hi> of <hi>Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Surrey</hi> is made Warden of all <hi>Scotland,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Creſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Treaſurer, and <hi>Branſly</hi> Chief Juſtice, to take in his name the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and fealties of all ſuch at held Lands of the Crown and to be General Guardian of the whole Kingdom. And notwithſtanding <hi>Balioll</hi> in Parliament with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the States of <hi>Scotland</hi> did tender his ſubmiſſion, and did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and ſwear fealty unto King <hi>Edward</hi> as his ſoveraign Lord, yet is he for his former infidelity ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſent into <hi>England:</hi> but not long after though the Scots were without an head, their King being in <hi>England,</hi> and all their great men in captivity and ſubjection, yet they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108759:56"/>wanted not an heart to ſhake off ſervitude, and animated by one <hi>William Wallis</hi> a poor private Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, though nobly deſcended, made an audacious and dangerous attempt, who with a forlorn and deſperate rabble like himſelf, fell ſuddenly on the Engliſh Officers, and ſlew Sir <hi>Hugh Creſſingham</hi> with ſix thouſand Engliſh, recovered many Caſtles, and regained the Town of <hi>Barwick.</hi> And ſeconded by ſucceſs ſo increaſed by ranging and rowling up and down, many of the nobler ſort reſorting to him, that within a ſhort ſpace his forces amounted to a copious and Warlike Army; and was in a propinque poſſibility to have freed his countrey from ſubjection, if the ſpeedy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of King <hi>Edward</hi> had not anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated him; who removing his Court to <hi>York,</hi> and making that City his imperial Seat, (as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperours heretofore did) that with the more convenience he might quell the inſulting Scots, there raiſed an exquiſite and choice Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108759:57"/>and with three thouſand men of Armes on barded horſes, and four thouſand others armed on horſe without bards; and with an Army of foot anſwerable, he encountred the confident Army of the <hi>Scots,</hi> who on the onſet made ſuch terrible ſhouts, that King <hi>Edwards</hi> Horſe frighted therewith caſt him off and brake two of his ribs, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he gets up again, goes on, and gains the victory. In which battel <hi>Sexaginta Scotorum millia occiſa fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt,</hi> threeſcore thouſand Scots were ſlain, as <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> numbers them, among which there were two hundred Knights; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Parliament being called at St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> moſt of the great men of that Kingdome (except <hi>Wallis</hi>) who had eſcaped by flight, proſtrated their homage and fealty to King <hi>Edward</hi> as their ſupream head and King, of which <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> giveth this character,
<q>Arma parant Scotus regno dolet eſſe remotus.</q>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:108759:57"/>And King <hi>Edward</hi> the better to keep ſome in ſubjection, and deter others from inſurrection, did confer moſt of the eſtates of the Earls and Barons of <hi>ſcotland</hi> with their titles that ſtood out, on the Engliſh, as a reward of their valour and vertue.<note place="margin">Holling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Ed. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And now it would ſeem that <hi>Scotland</hi> was quite conquer'd and ſubjected to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> they having no King nor Heir in <hi>Scotland</hi> but the King of <hi>England.</hi> But as <hi>Cambden</hi> ſaith, <hi>eſt Natio ſervitutis Impatientiſſimae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cambd. Brit.</note> It is a Nation im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of ſervitude, and a breeder of ſtubborn and refractory ſpirits, wich to their power would not ſtoop to the Engliſh Yoke: for though they were twice overthrown by King <hi>Edward,</hi> and thrice ſwore fealty unto him, yet did they as many times falſify their faith, which in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary affaires is principally to be maintained,
<q>Poſtremum eſt primumque t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eri Inter bella fidem.</q>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:108759:58"/>And now again go about to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive new commotions, rejecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Balioll</hi> their natural King, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he received the Crown upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſubject the Crown of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which they recalled their allegian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that they had given to him, and received <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> come of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecond branch, for their King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as one of their own writer ſaith, he had baſely condiſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to enſlave that Nation, to whom their liberty had alwaies been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dear,<note place="margin">In the Hiſtory of the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> that they have willingly and chearfully undergone all hazard of life and means; which if they ſhould have ſuffered, they had nothing lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereby they might be called men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and conſequently armed with this reſolution, under their new head and King, forced all the Wardens of <hi>Scotland</hi> to retire to <hi>Barwick,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as ſoon as the King heard, he ſends the Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and the Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> with a ſtrong power to relieve the Wardens of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whilſt he prepares a potent Army
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:108759:58"/>to ſollow, making a vow that either alive or dead he would pour venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince on the perfidious <hi>Scots.</hi> In which expedition, that magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous King falling into a ſickneſs at <hi>Carlile,</hi> adjured his ſon and all the Nobles about him upon their fealty, that if he died in this journey, they ſhould carry his corps with them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Scotland,</hi> and not ſuffer it to be interred until they had finally conquered the <hi>Scots;</hi> As <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury, Juſſit corpus ſuum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibi temauere inſepultum dum tota</hi> Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia <hi>eſſet finaliter acquiſita.</hi> An heroick reſolution worthy the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a conqueror; but he that never ſtooped to enemy was forced to ſubmit to Fate; and he that was alwaies victorious was overcome by death.
<q>
                  <l>Quae ſola ultricibus armis</l>
                  <l>Elat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s auimos fraenat, quae fortibus aequat</l>
                  <l>Imbelles, populiſque duces.</l>
               </q>
By whoſe immature <hi>obit</hi> the final
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108759:59"/>and entire conqueſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> was prevented, which in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility might have proſperouſly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, if the envious deſtinies h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not ſtopped the ſucceſs of his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or his ſucceeding ſon had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a truſty Executor of his Fathers T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtament: but he reſembled his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in vertue no more, then <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian</hi> did <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> or <hi>Commode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>toninus,</hi> and one day of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of <hi>Antony,</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more to be deſired then an whole Age of his. For he degenerating from his fathers worth, loſt all by ſloth and luxury, which his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had won by valour and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, permitting the new Scotch King to take all the Garriſons and Caſtles in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and without reſiſtance to enter the Engliſh borders, and to take and burn Towns; that unleſs he would ſuffer him to pull his crown from his head, he could doe no leſs then give him battel; and in a manner forced him for his honour to levy an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who like himſelf raiſed one
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108759:59"/>more fit for a court then a camp, which though it in number excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Scottiſh Army, was by it hamefully defeated, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and event of which would I could bury in oblivion, ſo much doth it ecclipſe the ancient glory of our Nation. Which ſingular victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſo encouraged the <hi>Scots,</hi> that for the ſpace of three hundred years they were emboldned almoſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any intermiſſion, to make War with the Engliſh, to their little loſſe and prejudice, and could never be throughly quieted and appeaſed until the happy arrival of <hi>James</hi> the King of <hi>Scots</hi> to the crown of <hi>England,</hi> upon which enſued a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed peace and union between thoſe two diſcordant and belligerant Nations, an hopeful union of both Kingdoms under one natural Liege Sovereign;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon.</hi> diſcourſe of that union.</note> at which the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation at the inſtant of his Majeſties reign became Deniſons, and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſtuati</hi> were naturalized Subjects of <hi>England</hi> from the time forward; and beſides it was a conjunction
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:108759:60"/>of Allegiance and Obedience of the Subjects of both Kingdoms due by nature to their Sovereign, which in ſubſtance is but the uniting of the hearts of the Subjects of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms one to the other under one Head and Sovereign,<note place="margin">Cok. L. <hi>7.</hi> Calvins caſe f. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> from which proceeded the union of protection of both Kingdoms, equally belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Subjects of either of them.</p>
            <p>Yet was not this Union ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute but that there were many ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and diſtinctions between them, as that they were diſtinct Kingdoms governed by ſeveral ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial and municipal laws, and had diſtinct and ſeparated Parliaments; for which reaſon the ſaid King with all the forces and faculties of his mind, wherein he ſurmounted his Predeceſſors, endeavoured more entirely to cement and conjoin them, eſpecially by laws, which are the ſinews of Societies. For as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> naturalization doth not take away the mark of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiner, but union of laws makes us
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108759:60"/>entire as our ſelves, which taketh away both deſtruction and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to that end called a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament without which it could not legally be brought to paſs. For as Sir <hi>Edw. Coke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cok. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Calvins <hi>caſe,</hi> f. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> a King that hath a Kingdom by deſcent, ſeeing by the Laws of that Kingdom he doth not inherit that Kingdome, he cannot change thoſe laws of himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of Parliament: which though ſolenmly propounded and ardently purſued by his Majeſty in Parliament, as alſo vigorouſly and judiciouſly ſeconded by many of the ableſt members of the houſe of Commons, yet were the ſubjects of this kingdome in this point ſo refractory and adverſe to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the other Kingdome, that no union during that Kings raign at any time, in any Parliament, though often times moved, could be voted, ordained, and eſtabliſhed,
<q>Auguſtis tamen excidit auſis.</q>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:108759:61"/>And therefore this union laſted not long for that it was not ſetled and pertected according to the aforeſaid principles and rules: neither had it ſo long laſted, but that, that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and circumſpect King did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thoſe two Emulous Nations in peace and unity, more by his mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificency and humanity, eſpecially towards the ſubjects of the other Kingdome, then by the politick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of union: by whoſe debonarity and bounty, the Scottiſh mens minds were ſo cloſely bound and knit unto him, that as well in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lend</hi> whilſt the King was abſent, no diſtaſt or diſcontent did break out among them, as alſo they forſook their ſtable confederacy with the French, which for many ages was the Source and Origin of impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and bloody battels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Engliſh and Scots; they being thereunto incited and aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed by the French: whereas whilſt the King reigned, the <hi>Scots</hi> had little Correſpondence with the French, and in civil comport ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:108759:61"/>to exceed the Engliſh, being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with them chearfully to conjo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their forces againſt the affronts of any enemy whether <hi>Spaniard,</hi> or <hi>French.</hi> In this peaceable poſture and union did King <hi>James</hi> leave the <hi>Scots</hi> when he left this light; But his Sonne ſucceeding wanted his Fathers Kings craft, and became too rigid towards the <hi>Scots,</hi> and though he knew them addicted to the reformed Religion and the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> diſcipline, yet would he obtrude upon them a book of common prayer framed by the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops, wherein was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned ſeveral ſeeds of idolatry, ſuperſtition &amp; falſe Doctrine as they averred; &amp; alſo a Canon annexed thereunto, that whoſoever ſhould oppoſe the ſame ſhould incurr the pain of excomunication, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers other canons fraught with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and ſuperſtitions, which won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly inflamed the <hi>Scots,</hi> and exaſperated them to raiſe ſeditions and to rebel againſt their King; for as <hi>Danaeus, propter mutatam a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:108759:62"/>vel publice vel privatim religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem patriam &amp; ob peregrinam ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptam, populus ſaepe a principe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſcit,</hi> For the changing of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of ones Countrey publiquely or privatly by the <hi>Prince,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a ſtrange one, the people doe often rebel againſt their <hi>Prince,</hi> as here it hapned; which they managed with ſuch violence and confidence, that a royall and terrible army of the Engliſh could not fright or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may them, but cunningly by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees drew the Engliſh into their faction, who unanimouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning did eradicate the Hierarchy of Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, book of common prayer and canons and the like trumpery in both Kingdomes, and for many years adhered to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and maintained a defenſive War againſt thoſe evil counſellors as ſeduced and withdrew his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty from his Parliament. But in the end the Scots fell into variance with the Parliament for many particular propoſitions concerning the intereſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:108759:62"/>and power of the King, and chiefly for going about to diminiſh the juſt power and greatneſs of his Majeſty, which they by their covenant (as was by them pretended,) their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and duty as ſubjects were obliged to ſupport; and thereupon in a grievous diſcontent without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their leaves left <hi>England</hi> and quite deſerted the Parliament. But not long after the fatal doom and death of the King eveening, which was juridically inflicted on him for his tyranny, to prevent ſucceeding tyranny;<note place="margin">As in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is expreſs'd.</note> the Parliament was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to the alteration in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to the ſetling the Government in a way of a free ſtate, which according to the practiſe of the Romans (whom in this tractate we have choſen for a preſident) was adjudged convenient and conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the good of this Nation, as it was for theirs, when for the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of <hi>Tarquinius Superbus,</hi> they did change their royal rule into the free commonwealth: neither doth ſuch a tranſmutation alter the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:108759:63"/>and eſſence of a ſtate, for the form of a commonwealth or city being changed, the commonwealth or city remaineth the ſame, <hi>Neque enim</hi> (as <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius</hi> ſaith) <hi>refert quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de gubernetur an rege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grotius de I B. &amp; P. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>an plurium, an multitudinis imperio, Idem enim eſt populus Romanus ſub Regibus, Conſulibus, &amp; Imperatoribus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it material how it is governed, whether by a King or by the command of more, or a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; but the formal difference conſiſteth in the quality and vertue of the Governours: for as learned and Judicious <hi>Patricius</hi> (who was born in a free City and did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe two elaborate and accurate <hi>Volumes,</hi> the firſt being in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a free State, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in praiſe of Principality, comparing the one with the other) affirmeth that if a Commonwealth be governed by one good man, that kind of Government, as it was the firſt ſo it is the beſt,<note place="margin">Patric. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rep. l. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but if through the vices and tyranny of the Prince, is be devolved into a free State,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:108759:63"/>ſuch Government is alſo to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and extolled leſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being factious, and carried away with luſt and avarice, ruine the eſtates of the beſt deſerved Citizens and will not be ſatisfied without the effuſion of blood, or baniſhment; which as the ſame Author ſaith was the overthrow of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and concludeth with the determination of <hi>Xenophon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Patric. de princ. l. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Omnes civiles civitates vitio eorum ruere, qui illis praeſunt,</hi> that all civil Cities are ruined by the vices of thoſe that have authority over them; for if they be rightly governed they may be <hi>omnino perpetuae &amp; immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales,</hi> alto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ether perpetual, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. But to return to the point whence my Penſtarted, the Scors incenſed with the diſmal and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death of their King, and total deprivation of his iſſue from the inheritance of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> began to muſter up in their mindes hoſtile thoughts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and to dream of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>England,</hi> they having a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:108759:64"/>title to it by their King, and many Cavaliers and Royaliſts dormant in that State vigorouſly to aſſiſt them. And therefore his Father being deprived of this life, they treated with <hi>CHARLES</hi> his Son and Heir, being then in Forreign parts, upon certain Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Covenants, to come and ſucceed his Father in that Crown; which he accepting, was royally by them received, and ſolemnly crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned KING of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And now the <hi>Scots</hi> proud of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive King, he being indeed a gallant <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and by reaſon of the civil Wars brought up in the field of <hi>Mars,</hi> began to prepare an Army for the Invaſion of <hi>England;</hi> of which the circumſpect Parliament having intelligence, all the actions of the Enemy being as equally known to them as their own; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the imminent danger which was eſteem'd great, (they being una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly united under one Head, who before were divided, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides aided by forreign Princes,)
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:108759:64"/>upon a ſerious debate created <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> for their General, as a man equivalent to ſo perilous a Deſign;<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> who <hi>Elatus gaudio</hi> (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was when by the conſult of the Senate he was decreed to march againſt the <hi>Gaules</hi> the ancient ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Rome</hi>) (to give him his due, without envy or flattery) with the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> celerity, and a compleat and well diſciplined Army marched up into the bowels of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wiſely projecting to make it the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Seat of War, and by provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Enemy to increaſe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Commilitons, and to diſhearten theirs; with whom was conjoined Lieut. Gen. <hi>Lambert due fulmina belli</hi> who in the end thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them all in pieces: but they in the beginning, though exceeding them in number, would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to hazard a battel, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by <hi>Fabian</hi> cunctations and deprivation of neceſſaries to weaken and diminiſh their forces, continually retreating and drawing them into mooriſh and unſound
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:108759:65"/>places, whereby many periſhed, and divers fell into pernicious diſeaſes, ſo as the General was conſtrained to retire with the reliques of his Army towards the Sea, with an intention to ſhip them for <hi>England;</hi> which the numerous Scottiſh Army con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, being well accompliſhed and furniſhed with ſound and able men, and ſufficient neceſſaries, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued them at the heels, and having cooped them up within a Nook of land and encompaſſed them within the Arms of the Sea, thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſure of ſpoil and victory, they boldly offered them battel: which the General and <hi>Lambert</hi> his Lieut. General, though environed with deſperate extremes,<note place="margin">Veget. de mili. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> cheerfully and couragiouſly embraced (<hi>Clauſis in deſperatione creſcit audacia</hi>) and with more then ordinary vigour and audacity, piouſly excited their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militons being but a wearied and ſick handful of men to that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate encounter, who reſolving to die or gain the victory ruſhed with them into the battel: And the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:108759:65"/>animating the Foot, and the Lieut. General <hi>Lambert</hi> the Horſe, under the Word and Name of the Lord of Hoſts, obteined a glorious and wondrous Victory, moſt of that mighty Army being ſlain, or taken priſoners,
<q>Dignos laude viros Muſa vetat mori.</q> Whereas if the Scots had permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to paſſe, and not forced them to fight upon ſuch deſperate ſtraits, and followed the military precept, <hi>cum deſperatis non eſt pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandum,</hi> they had made an inglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious return, and the Scots had gained a fortunate opportunity upon a conſequent Invaſion to have ſubdued <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Homcr. Ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>But God's will was done, and the General skilful how to uſe his Victory, with his victorious Army like an irreſiſtible inundation over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:108759:66"/>the whole Countrey, took <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and the Caſtles of <hi>Leith, Dundee, Brent</hi> Iſland; as alſo St. <hi>Johnſtons,</hi> and <hi>Sterling</hi> Caſtle, a place of incredible ſtrength, and in concluſion forced their hopeful KING, with the remainder of his forces ſecretly to fly into <hi>England</hi> for Refuge, upon vain hopes of ſecond ſupplies; but by the divine providence being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and ſtopping his courſe at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was by the invincible General, and his couragious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militons, who with tedious and irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome marches at the length over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took him, totally deſeated and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vanquiſhed: many Nobles of <hi>Scotland</hi> being taken, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with many thouſand other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour perſons. By which Victory the conqueſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely accompliſhed, and ever ſince hath been ſubject to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England;</hi> which by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that conqueſt have therein Placed Garriſons and Engliſh Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, according to the Roman Rule
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:108759:66"/>to contein them in ſubjection, peace and union. But to apply my Pen to the other rule which is the union by laws; and though it is in the power of the Conqueror at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to alter and change the laws of the conquered Kingdom,<note place="margin">Cok. L. <hi>7.</hi> Calvins caſe f. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> and that without a Parliament as <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt did by his Charter of <hi>Rutland,</hi> but until he doth make an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of laws, the ancient laws of that Kingdom do ſtill remain; yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is the greater victory to alter and change the Laws of the conquered with their conſent, that there may be a more intimatc and intire union between them. And therefore did the Parliament in <hi>December,</hi> 1651. to the end that the people of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould be united with the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into one Commonwealth and under one Government, ſend Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners into <hi>Scotland</hi> to invite the people of that Nation unto ſuch an happy union; who proceeded ſo far therein, that the Shires and Burroughes of <hi>Scotland</hi> by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:108759:67"/>appearing at <hi>Dalkeith,</hi> and again at <hi>Edenborough,</hi> did accept of the ſaid union and aſſent thereunto, which was ſeconded by the late Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> who by the advice of his council ordained, <hi>April</hi> 5. 1654. That all the Dominions of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of the Iſles and Territories thereunto belonging, are and ſhall be, and are hereby incorporated into, conſtituted and confirmed one Commonwealth with <hi>England,</hi> and in every Parliament held ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſaid Commonwealth, thirty perſons ſhall be called from, and ſerve for <hi>Scotland,</hi> which Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was confirmed by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the year 1657. So many Knights, and Burgeſſes, as before was expreſſed, who were called and ſummoned according to the ſaid Ordinance, were admitted to ſit in the ſaid Parliament, and did vote &amp; jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n with the Engliſh in the making and enacting of Laws; which Laws ſo made or hereafter to be made by them in Parliament, do bind and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:108759:67"/>oblige the Commons of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as well as the Commons of <hi>England;</hi> becauſe the Knights and Burgeſſes of both Countries, being choſen by the Aſſent of the Commons of either Countrey, do repreſent the eſtates of the ſeveral and diſtinct Commons of either Countrey: And therefore as St. <hi>German</hi> ſaith, every ſtatute there made,<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>&amp;</hi> Slud. li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> is of as ſtrong effect in law, as if all he commons were then preſent perſonally at the making thereof. There are many more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular clauſes in the aforeſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance contained, which concurr to the more full effecting of the ſaid union, all which I refer to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſupream council of this Nation. And though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the countreys of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> be ſuch, that there can hardly in all things be ſuch an obſolute reconciling and uniting of their laws, no more then there hath been between other country's ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the obedience and allegiance of the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> as <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> and <hi>Aquitany,</hi> had ſeveral
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:108759:68"/>lawes different to the lawes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; Garneſey</hi> and <hi>Jerſey</hi> have yet their ſeveral lawes, which for the moſt part were the antient lawes and cuſtoms of <hi>Normandy; Kent,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> have alſo their ſeveral Laws and cuſtoms, and ſo hath the county of <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Cheſter:</hi> yet do not theſe ſeveral Laws make any differences in matter of ſubjection and obedience, and are no markes of diſunion or ſeveral allegiances.</p>
            <p>Howſoever as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Diſcourſe of the union of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> it is to be wiſhed that the Scottiſh Nation was governed by our Lawes which with ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement are worthy to govern if it were the world; or elſe that <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be in the like degree and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions with <hi>Wales,</hi> as hath been for many hundred years; thoſe Laws and cuſtoms onely being in force, which are reaſonable and agreable to the Laws and cuſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> for it is a matter too curious to extirpate all particular cuſtoms which are conſonant to reaſon, and it ſufficeth that there
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:108759:68"/>be a uniformity in the fundamental Laws.</p>
            <p>For language it is not needful to infiſt upon it, becauſe both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are of one language, though of ſeveral dialects, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is ſo ſmall between them, as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth rather an enriching of our language then a continuance of two; ſo as it may ſeem convenient that as they Originally participate of one language, they ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be under one Government, as heretofore by antient Hiſtories they are reported to have been; which is now revived and like to continue, the premiſed Roman rules being obſerved.</p>
            <p>But now to waft <hi>Englands</hi> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring forces over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> which though it was firſt conquered is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Arrear, for that it is more remote, and ſeparated from it by the Sea; yet is it by <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſtiled <hi>Britaunia Minor</hi> as an adjacent Iſland, and is another <hi>Brittain,</hi> as <hi>Brittain</hi> is ſaid to be another world,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:108759:69"/>it being not inferiour to any part of <hi>Britanny</hi> for affinity and fertility, as <hi>Tacitus, ſolum, Coelumque &amp; inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia haut multum a Britannia diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vita Agr.</note> And indeed is endowed with many dowries of nature, with the fruitfulneſs of the ſoyl, and plenty of all proviſion, with the ports, the quarries, the woods, and other worthy materials. But yet it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der queſtion what King firſt ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated that Iſland, Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> maketh mention of an antient Charter of King <hi>Edgar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cokes pre. l. <hi>4. 4th Book of Reports.</hi>
               </note> in which he bleſſeth the altitonant and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God for all his victories, and that he had ſubjected all the Kingdomes of the Iſland of the Sea unto <hi>Norway</hi> with their fierceſt Kings, and the greateſt part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with its moſt noble City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> to the Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Huntington</hi> ſaith, there were five Kingdomes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> of which the great or greateſt part was conquered by King <hi>Edgar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gambd. Britttan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which <hi>Cambden</hi> alſo affirmeth, <hi>Quod maximam Hiberniae
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:108759:69"/>partem devicit,</hi> yet becauſe <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond made a more abſolute conqueſt of it, the honor of that conqueſt is aſcribed to him, and was the firſt was intituled <hi>Rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, Dominus Haberniae;</hi> and as <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Huntington</hi> Hiſtorieth it, at his Arrival with a potent Army into <hi>Ireland,</hi> the King of <hi>Cork,</hi> the King of <hi>Limmerick,</hi> the King of <hi>Oxery,</hi> and the King of <hi>Meth</hi> ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his ſummons, recognizing him to be <hi>totius Hiberniae dominum,</hi> (only the King of <hi>Conagh</hi> ſtood out) which Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> confirmed to him and his Heirs, and which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by his power was poſſeſſed, and detained by Engliſh Colonies.</p>
            <p>Yet was there no alteration of their Lawes till the reign of King <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn,</hi> who as Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the twelfth year of his raign went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and there by advice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grave and learned men in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aws whom he carried with him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Parliament <hi>de Communi omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> de <hi>Hibernia conſenſu</hi> enjoyned and eſtabliſhed, that <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:108759:70"/>be Governed by the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cok. Com. f. <hi>1.</hi> a. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> which he left in writing under his ſeal in the Exchequer of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and which afterwards was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Charter of <hi>Henry</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Davis rep. f. <hi>37.</hi> a <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> in the thirtieth year of his reign, wherein is declared, that for the common utility of the Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the unity of thoſe Lands, that all the Laws and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms that are holden in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England,</hi> be holden in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and that the ſame Lands be ſubject to the ſame Laws, and be ruled by them, as King <hi>John</hi> when he was there did firmly enjoyn; and therefore willed that all the writs of the common Law, which run in <hi>England,</hi> likewiſe run in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and accordingly was it reſolved <hi>Trin.</hi> 13. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>Coram rege in Theſaurie in lenge placite,</hi> that the ſame Laws ought to be in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England:</hi> and therefore as Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> ſaith, every County <hi>Palatine</hi> as well in <hi>Ireland</hi> as in <hi>England</hi> was originally parcel of the<note place="margin">Davis rep. f. <hi>6, 7. B.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:108759:70"/>ſame Realm, and derived of the Crown, and was alwaies governed by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and the Lands there were holden by ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and tenures, of which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law took notice, although the Lord had a ſeveral juriſdiction, and a ſigniory ſeparated from the Crown; upon conſideration of which Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> inferreth this concluſion,<note place="margin">Cok. Com. f. <hi>14.</hi> B.</note> that the unity of Laws is the beſt means for the unity of Countries as before hath been premiſed.</p>
            <p>Yet many of the Iriſh ſoon after, abſolutely refuſed the Engliſh Laws, preferring their Iriſh cuſtoms, which they call their <hi>Brehon</hi> Law, becauſe the Iriſh call their Judges <hi>Brehons;</hi> and therefore in the Parliament <hi>Anno</hi> 40. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Cok. ib.</note> In the Parliament holden at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> before <hi>Lionell</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> being the Lieutenant of that Realm; the <hi>Brehon</hi> Laws were declared to be no Law, but a lewd cuſtom, which fot that reaſon were aboliſhed, <hi>Quia malus uſus eſt abolendus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:108759:71"/>
            <p>And though that by that ſtatute the <hi>Brehon</hi> Law, which was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of the Iriſh, was declared to be no Law, yet was it not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely aboliſhed among the meer Iriſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Davis</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, <hi>f.</hi> 39</note> but only prohibited and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to be uſed among the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh race, and the meer Iriſh were left at large to be ruled by their barbarous cuſtoms as before: And therefore for that by thoſe cuſtoms, baſtards had their part with the legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, &amp; women were altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from <hi>Dower,</hi> &amp; that the daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters were not inheritable, though their Fathers dyed without Males; by the ſame ſtatute it was Enacted, that no compaternity, Education of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, or Marriages, be made or had between the Engliſh and others in peace with the King, with the meer Iriſh. And though the ſtatute made by King <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Ordinance and writ of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third were general, yet is it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by all the antient Records of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> was onely put in execution in that part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:108759:71"/>reduced and devided into counties and poſſeſſed by the Engliſh Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,<note place="margin">Vid. Davis <hi>39.</hi> a. o.</note> and not in the Iriſh Counties and territories which were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into Counties until the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> For King <hi>John</hi> made but twelve Counties, but the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and territories which are divided into 21. Counties at large, being then inhabited for the moſt part by meer Iriſh, were out of the limits of any Shire ground by the ſpace of three hundred years after the making of the former twelve Counties, for it was impoſſible that the common Law of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be executed in thoſe Counties, or territories; for the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> cannot be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where the writ of the King doth not run, but where there is a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Sheriffe or other Miniſters of the Law to ſerve, and return the writs of the King: and for this cauſe were the meer Iriſh out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the King, becauſe the Law of the King, and his writs as
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:108759:72"/>
               <hi>Littleton</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Littl. Tom. f. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> are the things by which a man is protected &amp; aided; and therefore the meer Iriſh, (who had no the benefit of the Law un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight) where any mention is made of the Wars of <hi>Ireland</hi> are culled enemies, &amp; the engliſh rebels but by the 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1. by which it is recited that becauſe the King of <hi>England</hi> did not aſſume the name &amp; ſtile of King, the Iriſh Inhabitants have not been ſo obedient to the King of <hi>England</hi> and his Laws, as of right they ought to have been; It was Enacted that King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, his Heirs and Succeſſors ſhall be for ever Kings of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſhall have the name ſtile and title of the King of that land, with all the honors, prerogatives, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, appertayning to the State and Majeſty of a King, as united, and annexed to the imperiall Crown. After which royall union the ſaid difference of the Engliſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells and Iriſh enemies is not to be found on Record, but all thoſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:108759:72"/>meer Iriſh were afterwards reputed and accepted ſubjects and Leigemen to the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> and had the benefit and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the law of England. And afterwards the Iriſh were more averſe from Rebellions, and more ready to forſake their <hi>Brehon</hi> laws and to be ruled by ours, the ſtile and title of the King of <hi>Ireland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more pleaſing &amp; acceptable to them then Lord of <hi>Ireland;</hi> the one denoting a tyrannical &amp; arbitrary Government,<note place="margin">Tholoſ. Syntag. li. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> &amp; the other a limited power according to law and equity. For ſuch Princes as arrogate to themſelves the name of Lords, ſeem to uſurp an arbitrary and plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiary power over their ſubjects, which are Proprietors of nothing but at the will of their great Lord. And therefore did the wiſeſt of the Boman Emperors refuſe to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that arrogant and abſolute title,<note place="margin">Davis f. <hi>40.</hi> B.</note> it properly appertaining only to God: but under a King the ſubjects are free men, and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in their Goods and Frank te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements and inheritance; who
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:108759:73"/>doth not domineer over them according to his will and pleaſure, but ruleth them according to Law, for as <hi>Bracton, Non eſt Rex ubi domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur voluntas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> fol. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; non Lex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly the Kings and Queens of <hi>England</hi> to the intent that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> might have a free courſe in and through all the Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the ſtatute of 11. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 9.) did they provide in ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments to wit, 3. &amp; 4. <hi>Ph.</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> c. 3. and 11. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 9. that Commiſſions ſhould be awarded to reduce into Shires and hundreds all the Iriſh Land which were not Shire ground before. And according to it in the ſeveral Governments of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Earl</hi> of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Sidney</hi> and Sir <hi>John Perott,</hi> not only the Iriſh territories in the confines of <hi>Lemſter,</hi> but alſo the entire provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Conagh</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> being out of all Shire ground before, were divided and diſtinguiſhed into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Counties and hundreds, &amp; ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sheriffs, Coroners, and juſtices of peace, and other Officers and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:108759:73"/>Miniſters of the Law of <hi>England</hi> have been from time to time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in thoſe Counties, by ſeveral patents and commiſſions under the great ſeal of <hi>England:</hi> and by this means has the common Law of <hi>England</hi> been communicated to all perſons and executed throughout all that Realm for many years paſſed; and ſo continued unto the reign of the late King <hi>James,</hi> who alſo by a ſpecial proclamation in the third year of his reign, declared and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed that he had received all the Natives of the Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> into his royal protection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which it was clearly reſolved, that the common Law of <hi>England</hi> was eſtabliſhed univerſally throughout the Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that all perſons and poſſeſſions within that Realm ought to be governed by the rules of that Law, and that every ſubject ſhall inherit his Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the juſt and honourable law of <hi>England,</hi> in that manner and by the ſame law that the King inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the Crown of <hi>Irelaud:</hi> and by
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:108759:74"/>theſe degrees was the common law of <hi>England</hi> introduced and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the ſame year of that King accordingly, it was by the ſpecial order of the deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the juſtices reſolved and declared, that becauſe all the Iriſh counties and the Inhabitants of them were to be governed by the rules of the common law of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Davis re. f. <hi>51.52</hi>
               </note> the Iriſh cuſtoms were void in law, not only for the inconvenience and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of them; but for that they were meer perſonal cuſtomes and could not alter the deſcent of inheritance. For all the poſſeſſions of the Iriſh territories (before the common law of <hi>England</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed) did run either in the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and courſe of Taniſtry, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by every Lordſhip or chiefty with the portion of land which did paſs with it, did go without partition to the taniſt and not to the next Heir of the Lord or chieftye, but to the elder and more worthy of that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, who oftentimes was removed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:108759:74"/>and expelled by another, who was more active and more ſtrong then he. Beſides the wives of the ſigniory claimed to have a ſole property in a certain portion of goods during the coverture, with power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of them without the aſſent of their husbands: Or in the courſe and cuſtom of Gavel kind, whereby all the inferiour tenancies were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible among the males, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the Cauſeny or chief of that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage who was commonly moſt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, after the death of every tennant which had a competent portion of land did aſſemble all of that linage, and having put all their poſſeſſions in Hotch Potch, did make a new partition of all, in which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition he did not aſſign to the Sons of thoſe that dyed the portion that the Father had, but he allotted to every one of that linage according to his Antiquity the more and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part; by whom alſo a new par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition upon the death of every infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Tenant was made at his will and diſcretion. And ſo by reaſon
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:108759:75"/>of thoſe frequent partitions and tranſlation of Tenants from one portion to another, all the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were uncertain, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the poſſeſſions was the true cauſe that no civil habitation were erected, no incloſure or improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was made of Lands in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> counties where this cuſtome was in uſe; eſpecially in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> which ſeemed throughout to be a Wilderneſs before the new Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers there.</p>
            <p>Alſo by that cuſtome baſtards had their purparty with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the women were utterly excluded from Dower, the daughters were not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritable though their Father died without Iſſue male: and therefore for the aforeſaid inconveniences and unreaſonableneſs of thoſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, were they utterly aboliſhed; As the cuſtoms of Gavel kind in <hi>North-Wales</hi> by <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt and <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. which were ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable to the cuſtoms of the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> and therefore was it adjudged that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:108759:75"/>the lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould deſcend according to the courſe of the the common law, that women ſhall be endowed, that daughters ſhall be inheritable for defect of iſſue male; and the property of ſuch goods ſhould be in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lords and not in the feme coverts according to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> uſage: which reſolution of the Judges, by Order of the Deputy was regiſtred among the acts of the Council; but this proviſion was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, That if any of the meer <hi>Iriſh</hi> had poſſeſſed and enjoyed any portion of land by theſe cuſtoms, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the commencement of the reign of the late King <hi>James,</hi> that he ſhall not be diſturbed in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſion, but ſhall be continued and eſtabliſhed in it; but that after the commencement of his reign, all land, ſhall be adjudged to deſcend to the Heirs by the Common Law, and ſhall hereefter be poſſeſſed and enjoyed accordingly. And yet were not the laws of <hi>England</hi> fully and rotally eſtabliſhed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> one of the main triangles of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:108759:76"/>laws of <hi>England</hi> being yet excluded, for as Sir <hi>Edw. Coke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cok. Gom. <hi>on</hi> Litt. <hi>110.</hi> B.</note> the laws of <hi>England</hi> are devided into common Law, Cuſtoms, and Statute law; and though the common law of <hi>England</hi> was introduced, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes aboliſhed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet were not the Statutes made in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> currant in that countrey; for the Land of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had Parliaments, made Law and changed laws, and thoſe of that land were not obliged by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they did not ſend Knights to it, as Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi> obſerveth.<note place="margin">Cok. Com. f. <hi>141.</hi> B.</note> And though Sir <hi>Edward Poynings</hi> having both Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and Civil power given him by the commiſſion of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh above the Earl of <hi>Kildare</hi> then De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bacon Hen. <hi>7.</hi> f. <hi>138.</hi>
               </note> called a Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein was made that memorable Act, which at this day is called <hi>Poynings</hi> Law, whereby all the Statutes of <hi>England</hi> were made to be of force in <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were not, neither are any now in force in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which were
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:108759:76"/>made in <hi>England</hi> ſince that time, but have had Parliaments ſince holden there, wherein they have made divers particular Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Government of that Domiuion; wherefore in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Ireland</hi> was ſtill a Dominion divided, and ſeparated from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the union between thoſe two Nations in that reſpect not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely perfect; and therefore did it ſeem a worthy Act in the late Protector to have ordained by the advice of his Council, that thirty Knights and Burgeſſes out of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould be elected to ſit in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> thereby to oblige thoſe of that countrey to be ſubject and obedient to our ſtatute as well as our common Laws, that as we are one and the ſame common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſo we may be governed by one and the ſame Laws, and they participate of the ſame honours and priviledges, which is the ſureſt means for the conſolidation of ſuch a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the more entire the union is, the leſs apt will they be upon
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:108759:77"/>any occaſions to break, and the imperfection of ſuch a union being oftentimes the Origine and cauſe of Revolts: a direful example of which is recorded in the Annals of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Republick, which as it was the beſt eſtate in the world, ſo is it the beſt example; which as in the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpice we have followed, ſo will we not forſake to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aneus Martius</hi> was the firſt that conquered the Latins, who having by force taken many of their Towns, received many thouſands of them into the City of <hi>Rome</hi> as one body, but becauſe they were not equally intreated, they joyned Armes with the <hi>Tarquinians</hi> againſt the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and though after a bloody battail they were reunited, yet was not that union durable, becauſe not entire; for that the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had not inſerted them in their Tribes, nor admitted them to participate of their immunities and honours; for which reaſons the Latins conceiving themſelves to be undervalued and vilified, were
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:108759:77"/>bold to demand the freedom of the city of Rome, and that one of their conſuls be of their countrey, which being denyed they converted their demands into Armes. Yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being again reconciled, upon hopes to be enfranchiſed; firſt by <hi>Fabius Flaccus</hi> one of the conſuls who attempted the prorogation of the Law though impeded by the Senate, and afterwards by <hi>Livius Bruſus,</hi> who was alſo oppoſed by the people: at which exaſperated ſeeing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deluded, they made an aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation with the <hi>Hetrurians</hi> and the <hi>Sabius,</hi> who becauſe they were all by affinity of promiſcuous marriages conſanguineans, and as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Florus l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>unum corpus</hi> with the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that they had aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented that city by their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and yet were diſpiſed, they jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intly made War againſt the City of Rome, as well thoſe who lived in the City, as thoſe who abided in <hi>Italy,</hi> which was called <hi>Bellum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale,</hi> but indeed <hi>bellum civile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid,</note> aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and deſtructive War both to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:108759:78"/>the people of <hi>Rome</hi> and the Cities of <hi>Italy,</hi> that as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nec Annibalis, nec Py<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rhi fuit tanta vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio,</hi> the devaſtation and depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Hanniball</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> was not ſoe great, ſuch were the fatall fruits of an imperfect union. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the people of <hi>Rome</hi> inſtructed by fad experience did condiſeend to a more intire union with them, and permitted them to participate of the priviledges and honors of <hi>Rome,</hi> being according to their worth preferred and placed in the Senate; which <hi>Claudius</hi> in <hi>Tacitus</hi> urgeth in the like caſe, for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the chiefeſt of the French into the Senate in theſe words, <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim ignoro Iulios Alba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. l. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caruncanios Camerio, Portios Tuſculo, &amp; ne vetera ſcrutemur, Etruria, Lucania<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; omni Italia in Senatum accites. Caeter a quis neſeit?</hi> And needs no application.</p>
            <p>But in this caſe the ſovereign uſe of the Law hath almoſt made me to omit the neceſſity of Arms, and to demonſtrate how through the inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency and debility of Engliſh
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:108759:78"/>Colonies and the <hi>Militia</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a deteſtable and infernal deſign was hatched and contrived by the rebellious and bloody Papiſts, whereby all the Forts and Magazins in that Kingdom were to be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in one day, and all the Engliſh Proteſtants maſſacred, and all <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in one day to be loſt, had it not through the providence of God, the very night before been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by one only Iriſh man, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to one Sir <hi>John Clotworthy</hi> whom <hi>Macmahon</hi> had unadviſedly truſted with the Plot: by which <hi>Dublin</hi> was ſaved and the ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure of the Caſtle, the Kingdomes chief Magazine prevented, to which purpoſe many rebels of great note came to the City the day before, who upon the apprehenſion of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahon</hi> eſcaped with the Lord <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> that night, to do more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; &amp; with the reſt of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators that were that day in all the country round about, within two months ſpace murthered 200000 proteſtanes; many of them being
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:108759:79"/>by intollerable tortures brought to their end, beſides infinit numbers who were robbed and ſpoiled of all they had, and daily driven naked and almoſt famiſhed to <hi>Dublin</hi> for reliefe; with whom the City was ſoc filled that they were enforced for the preſervation of themſelves and the lives of their wives, children and families, to fly for ſuccour into the ſeverall parts of the Dominions of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O nullo ſcelus credibile in avo</l>
               <l>Quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſteritas negot.<note place="margin">Sen 'c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Toyeſt.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>It equalling, if not exceeding in number and cruelty, the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and perfidious Maſſacre of the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Paris.</hi> For <hi>Ireland</hi> being deſtitute of a Deputy and military guards, <hi>Hinc Hiberniae calamitas:</hi> the Lord Juſtices, Sir <hi>William Perſons,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace</hi> were driven to take thoſe Arms which they found in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and to arm whom they could of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to defend themſelves and the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:108759:79"/>places near, againſt the approach of the enemy. In this dangerous ſtreight and perillous condition did the eſtates of the Engliſh in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtand, who for want of a ſetled ſtation of Engliſh Colonies were at the point to have loſt themſelves, and that Countrey; for the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh were ſo involved in homebred civil Wars, that the Parliament of England for a preſent aid could ſend them but twenty thouſand pounds, and though afterwards, they tranſported ſome Regiments, yet for the ſpace of ten years were they unable to free that countrey from that malignant and peſtilent enemy. The <hi>Trojan</hi> Wars being incomparable to it for cruelty, for through our daily diſcords and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions their curſed cruel crue continually augmented almoſt to the overwhelming and deſtruction of the Engliſh. But when all the malignants were quelled in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Royaliſts debelled in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that <hi>Dublin</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the Iriſh with a formidable
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:108759:80"/>Army and in danger of a ſurrender, General <hi>Cromwell</hi> was ſent by the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to relieve <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſuppreſs the Iriſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; at whoſe approach Colonel <hi>Jones</hi> encouraged, made an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and ſuddain ſally on the enemy, and valiantly repelling them, put them all to flight; which the General purſuing, within a ſhort ſpace byſnarp ſiedges regained thoſe ſtrong Towns and Garriſons which the Iriſh had ſurreptitiouſly ſurprized, and by degrees cleared the countrey of ſuch ſeditious Iriſh as ſeduced and corrupted the well affected of that Nation, and having ſetled it in peace and ſafety, at his return was honoured with the thanks of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>And now the provident Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment apprehending it more ſafe and advantagious to prevent commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then to ſuppreſs them, ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and appointed Engliſh Colonies to be deduced into <hi>Ireland,</hi> which they committed firſt to the charge of Lieutenant General <hi>Ireton,</hi> and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:108759:80"/>after his death to the Marſhalling of Lieutenant General <hi>Charles Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> who afterwards for his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar care and vigilancy was by the Lord Protector made Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> both of them being ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſively Commanders in chief of a competent Army, and of all the Garriſons ſufficiently fortifyed; and to ſtrike the more terror into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, they cenſured the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of that Rebellion with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital punniſhment, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t poena ad pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, metus ad omnes perveniat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cok. Com.</note> And confiſcated all the lands and goods of ſome, and ſequeſtrated others to the uſe of the Commonwealth, by which Roman <hi>Model, Ireland</hi> ever ſince hath been ruled and preſerved in peace and unity, the Engliſh language alſo being through conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual commerce the common ſpeech among them.</p>
            <p>To draw all to period. By this I hope it is made perſpicuous that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Kingdoms upon conqueſt, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which baſis the moſt parts of ſuch unions have been founded, being
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:108759:81"/>purchaſed by valour, are poſſeſſed and ſetled by the ſweetneſs of cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, power of Armes, ſeverity of cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, power of Armes, ſeverity of Laws, and communication of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which is fully demonſtrated by that univerſal union of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Orb, as by the particular u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>England, Wales, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which is by thoſe means ſo compleatly perfected, and by the proweſs and prudence of the Parliament and it's Conquering Champions fetled, that as it was worthily vowed by the late King <hi>James, faciam cos In gentem unam,</hi> which indeed he did endeavour to have effected; ſo it may be truly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verred of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Quod fecit cos in gentem u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that it hath made thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countries one Nation, which the premiſed Roman courſe being obſerved, may ſo remain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, <hi>Dum coelum &amp; ſtellae eandem rationem obtinent,</hi> whilſt the Sun and Stars run the ſame courſe.</p>
            <p>With this hypothetical caution, if union be ſoftred and cheriſhed
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:108759:81"/>among our ſelves, and ambitious and envious diſcord ſhnaned, which as a ſwelling and eminent Rock, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſheth in pieces, the firmeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth approaching it, &amp; which was the ruine of the Roman com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth it ſelf as the <hi>Venuſine</hi> Poet.
<q>Suis &amp; ipſa Roma viribus ruit.<note place="margin">Hor. e. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note>
               </q> And therefore let us lay aſide all occaſions of diffidence and ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which may breed diſcord and diſſention, and remember the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that if you bite and devour one another, take heed you be not conſumed one of another; for <hi>humana Conſilia Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtig antur, ubi divinis praeferuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hath the Author rudely wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a difficult work, which deſerves a finer thread and a neater Artiſt, yet propoſing truth for his end, he hopeth it may countenance the ſimplicity of the ſtile,<note place="margin">Cok. li. <hi>10.</hi> ep.</note> for <hi>veritatis ſermo ſimple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and his labour what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is,<note place="margin">Tacit. Agr.</note> for the profeſſion of truth <hi>aut laudatus, aut excuſatus erit,</hi> yet
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:108759:82"/>reſpecting himſelf, he is ſo far from the imagination of praiſe, that he ſhall conceive himſelf favourably dealt withal, if he may find par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his preſumption.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108759:82"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
